<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sionis reductio, &amp; exultatio. Or, Sions return out of captivity with Sions reioycing for her return. A discourse, intended for the solemn festivity of the English nation, at Livorno in Italy, upon the happy news of King Charles the Second his return into England, which was there celebrated with munificent feasting, and magnificent shows, fire-works, and other signs of triumph, three days together, in the month of July anno Dom. 1660. Since occasionally preached in part, at St. Margarets in Westminster, the Sonday [sic] after the solemnization of the Kings birth-day, and entry into London; and now presented to publick view, as to correct the mis-apprehension, and mis-interpretation of some that were present; so to prevent the mis-information, and depravation of others that were absent. By Ro. le Grosse, cleric. An orthodox priest of the Church of England; and D. Oecumenical, then residing in Livorno, at his return from grand Cairo in Egypt.</title>
            <author>Le Grosse, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833282</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2173:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sionis reductio, &amp; exultatio. Or, Sions return out of captivity with Sions reioycing for her return. A discourse, intended for the solemn festivity of the English nation, at Livorno in Italy, upon the happy news of King Charles the Second his return into England, which was there celebrated with munificent feasting, and magnificent shows, fire-works, and other signs of triumph, three days together, in the month of July anno Dom. 1660. Since occasionally preached in part, at St. Margarets in Westminster, the Sonday [sic] after the solemnization of the Kings birth-day, and entry into London; and now presented to publick view, as to correct the mis-apprehension, and mis-interpretation of some that were present; so to prevent the mis-information, and depravation of others that were absent. By Ro. le Grosse, cleric. An orthodox priest of the Church of England; and D. Oecumenical, then residing in Livorno, at his return from grand Cairo in Egypt.</title>
                  <author>Le Grosse, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Leach,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year M DC LXII. [1662]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title words: "Reductio, &amp; exultatio" joined by left brace.</note>
                  <note>With imprimatur on verso of title page dated 24. Aug. 1662.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ [chi]¹ *²  B⁴ C²  D-I⁴ (-I4); [chi]1 blank.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained; MS. notes on p. 46.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1668 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulersl --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Sionis Reductio, &amp; Exultatio.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>Sions RET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN</hi> out of CAPTIVITY: WITH <hi>Sions</hi> REIOYCING for Her RETURN.</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE, Intended for the Solemn Feſtivity of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, at <hi>Livorno</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> upon the happy news of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second his Return into <hi>England,</hi> which was there celebrated with Munificent Feaſting, and Magnificent Shows, Fire-works, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſigns of Triumph, three days together, in the Month of <hi>July, Anno Dom.</hi> 1660. Since occaſionally preached in part, at St. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Sonday after the Solemnization of the Kings Birth-Day, and Entry into <hi>London;</hi> and now preſented to publick view, as to correct the miſ-apprehenſion, and miſ-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of ſome that were preſent; ſo to prevent the miſ-infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and depravation of others that were abſent.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ro. le Groſſe,</hi> Cleric. An Orthodox Prieſt of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and D. Oecumenical, then reſiding in <hi>Livorno,</hi> at his return from <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Fructus liberationis eſt laetitia; laetitiae autem fructus gratiarum actio. Laetari eſt multis; gaudere non niſi bonis.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Tho: Leach,</hi> in the Year MDCLXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex Aed. Sabaud. <date>
                     <hi>24. Aug. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G. Stradling Reverend. in Chr. Patr. Gilb. Epiſc. Lond. Sacel. Domeſticus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:2"/>
            <head>TO His moſt Illuſtrious Highneſs, RUPERT, Prince Palatine of the <hi>Rhene;</hi> Duke of <hi>Cumberland;</hi> Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and one of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR, May it pleaſe your Highneſs.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving had the Honour to wait upon Your Highneſs at <hi>Tolon,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and from thence to be remanded by Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into <hi>Italy,</hi> about ſome affairs concerning his Majeſties Service in thoſe parts, whiles <hi>I</hi> was abroad: <hi>I</hi> ſhould be moſt groſſely incivil, if I ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:37758:3"/>not tender thoſe due reſpects of Service, which I am able to expreſs to Your Highneſs, now I am come home. Not that I do, or can imagine Your Highneſs, any ways, to ſtand in need of my Service; But that by my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Your Highneſs, I may the better ſerve my ſelf and have better eſteem in the eys of others. <hi>Multa ideo habentur ſancta,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pliny,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Trajane</hi> the Emperour) <hi>quia Templis ſunt dicata<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And I ſee it verified by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that many men are accounted great, and in reputation, becauſe they have relation to, and are in the Service of great men. But alas! What ſervice can I perform to Your Highneſs? <hi>I</hi> can do nothing, now, but pray; and that <hi>I</hi> ſhall; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi> ſometimes, in another caſe; firſt to God for Your Highneſs, that he would bleſs and protect You; then to Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for my Self, and this poor miſ-reported Sermon; that You would pleaſe, according to Your wonted goodneſs, to caſt an eye of favour upon me, and protect it. The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of its compoſure was, the happy news of His Majeſties happy return into his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, whiles <hi>I</hi> was abroad: and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of its dedication to Your Highneſs, is,
<pb facs="tcp:37758:3"/>the unhappy entertainment it hath received from the Pulpit, ſince <hi>I</hi> came home. There <hi>I</hi> conceived it, here <hi>I</hi> preached it: So that, though it was a Forraigner in its conception; yet it is a Denizon in its production. The Subject of it, is, <hi>Our</hi> Sions <hi>Return out of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity,</hi> by reaſon of His MAJESTIES Return unto his Throne. And the duty it doth enforce to my ſelf and others, redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of our former Captivity, is our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful joyfulneſs, and joyful thankfulneſs to God for both. It hath met with much miſ-apprehenſion, and ſiniſter inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, by ſome, that are not well-wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to <hi>Sions</hi> proſperity: but would rather She ſhould remain in Captivity and in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than be bleſſed with the preſent liberty and felicity, which, through Gods bleſſing ſhe doth enjoy (and long may ſhe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the enjoyment of it!) by the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Raign of his SaCRed Majeſty; And ſo, by reaſon of their malign aſpect to, and diſ-reſpect of the Church, they do as much as Malice and the Devil can ſuggeſt unto them, aſperſe, traduce, and calumniate, all ſuch as are Conformable, and Orthodox Church-men. For vindication therefore of
<pb facs="tcp:37758:4"/>my Self, and this Sermon, honeſtly intended, but maliciouſly traduced, <hi>I</hi> have been neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to make it publick, which <hi>I</hi> thought ſhould ſtill continue private; and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to open view, as to correct the miſ-apprehenſion of ſome that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent when it was delivered, ſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the depravation of others that were abſent, and ſo miſ-informed. And thus, coming from the Pulpit to the Preſſe, in the plain dreſſe of Loyalty and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, <hi>I</hi> do, with all ſubmiſſion, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſelf, with it, to Your Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Highneſſe; And do humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Your Highneſs, that as You have been a Peerleſſe Champion of both, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Enemies of GOD, and the KING; ſo You will vouchſafe it, now fleeing in theſe robes for refuge to Your Quarters, a favourable acceptance, and a gracious Protection. And thus ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd under Your Highneſs tuition, it will go abroad ſecure from all black-mouthd aſperſion. In confidence of which Princely Favour, according to Your innate godneſſe, <hi>I</hi> do further addreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:37758:4"/>my ſelf to the Throne of Grace, and ſhall continually ſollicite the Prince of Princes, with my Prayers, that he will ſtill grace Your Highneſſe, with encreaſe of Honour here; and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver honour Your Highneſs, with the perfection of happineſs hereafter. So prayeth,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſes moſt humbly devoted, and Religiouſly addicted, Oratour and Servant,</hi> Ro: le Groſſe.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:6"/>
            <head>To his Honoured Friends, Mr. <hi>James</hi> and <hi>George Man,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Prime Merchants, but always the Royal Entertainers of the KINGS real Friends, at <hi>Livorno</hi> in <hi>ITALY.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Sermon, though it be primarily Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Prince, whom you did always ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; yet of right it doth moſt properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to you, who have been like Princes in the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of the Kings Friends (for which I can ſay, you too much ſuffered then, if not ſtill, by reaſon of the then prevailing times) whiles they were in exile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment abroad, and being in <hi>Italy.</hi> Amongſt which, I cannot but ingenuouſly confeſs, though I was one of the moſt unworthy, yet I was, without any Relation, or Letters of Credit and Commendation to you (the only ſupporters of Gentlemen in their Travels) moſt worthily entertained, and for many years, when I was in <hi>Italy;</hi> ſtill foſtered by you. In my laſt being with you, at my return from Grand <hi>Cairo</hi> (when after our Conflict with three Spaniſh men of War, being ſet upon by them, in the good Ship <hi>Recoverie,</hi> having diſcomfited the other two, we brought in the third, the great <hi>Alexander,</hi> their Admiral, with triumph in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Liverno</hi>) upon the happy news of His Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into His Kingdoms, this Treatiſe was conceived in your Houſe: In your Houſe it was framed and compoſed; and in your Houſe, if occaſion had ſerved, it ſhould have been delivered. But that which oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity then would not permit me to Preach, having
<pb facs="tcp:37758:7"/>been, (as you very well know,) delated into the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> by ſome ill-confiding Brethren, for Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once before, (though not in your Houſe,) there, neceſſity doth enforce me now, having preached it, for vindication of my ſelf againſt ſome Phanaticks, to Print it here. So that, though I could not preach it before you, where it was conceived; yet, being now in Print, I could not but, by way of gratitude, preſent it unto you, by whom (though you knew not of it) it was foſter'd. I know, if it were longer, it would come far ſhort of acceptance, in point of requital for thoſe favours which I have received; and yet I know your ingenuity to be ſuch, that being as it is, you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it, as a teſtimony of my gratitude. I ſhould, I confeſs, long e're this, have otherwiſe expreſſed my thankfulneſs, if either I had been reſtored to my own, (which, though it was given me by my Princes favour, His SaCRed Majeſty of happy memory, is ſtill unjuſtly kept from me by ſome of His verSHute, and verſatile Subjects) or ſettled in ſome other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. But the late Parliament, <hi>An.</hi> 1660. (as is ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted,) not permitting the one; and my hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, (becauſe I came home alone, and not accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with yellow Pages to aſſiſt me) not indulging the other; I cannot make thoſe Returns of gratitude, which I then intended, and would ſtill, if ability were anſwerable to my will, yet ſee performed: But here <hi>Ovids</hi> Apology muſt intercede, and make excuſe for me:— <hi>In magnis est voluiſſefatis:</hi> or if you pleaſe, <hi>Sit voluiſſe, ſat valuiſſe.</hi> However, that I might not ſhew my ſelf to be <hi>Ingratus Hoſpes,</hi> (as ſometimes <hi>Philip,</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> did inure a Souldier of his with that ſtigmatical cenſure,) I had rather, coming lately from exilement, in this exile and low condition, in which I am, expoſe my ſelf, in the eys of the now fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigious, and faſtidious world, to be diſgraceful, than
<pb facs="tcp:37758:7"/>any ways be thought to be unthankful. Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Gentlemem, (my worthy, and never to be forgotten friends,)</hi> I make this my addreſs to you now, with my firſt-fruits from the Preſs, ſince I came into <hi>England;</hi> and till ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe God to meliorate my fortunes, whereby I may endeavour to requite you with deeds, I do deſire you to accept of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Return of words. Yet think not, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that I do intend to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you only with windy words for your good deeds; or to fopp you off with verbal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions for your real actions: But aſſure your ſelves (and I do enter into Bond before the world for the performance) if ever ability on my part will permit; and occaſion on your part ſhall require it; I ſhall, with a grateful Metamorphoſis, transform theſe words into deeds; and turning letters into factures, (which yet are both required in your Factory) I ſhall inveſt theſe vocal and ſounding words, into ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and ſound works. In the mean time, I ſhall diſpatch my wiſhes, which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (if I may ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that Phraſe of <hi>Homer</hi>) as ſo many winged meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engers to the <hi>White-Hall</hi> of Heaven, thereto impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the King of Kings, who is the Author and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of all good things; (who can make <hi>Job,</hi> and all others, of rich men to become poor; and of poor men to become rich again, as he did him, at his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,) that he will repair your great loſſes with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duplication of your former fortunes, and temporal bleſſings, here in this life; and repay your curieſies to me, and to others, which we can never do, with eternal bleſſedneſs in the life that is to come. <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> theſe are the darlings of his wiſhes for you, who acknowledgeth himſelf to have been, and ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelf to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obliged Friend, to ſerve you,</hi> Ro: le Groſſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:8"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER!</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Andid Reader, ſo I call thee, for ſo I would have thee: whoe're thou beeſt, that ſhalt read this mangled, and miſ-reported Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; I deſire thee to read it, <hi>Non limis, ſed imis oculis:</hi> not with an oblique, crooked, or ſquint eye: As ſome did hear it, <hi>Auribus incultis, &amp; non rectè diſpoſitis:</hi> with ears not well picked, but impoſtumated, and not well diſpoſed: but read it rightly, read it throughly, and read it impartially. And ſo, being unbyaſſed in thy affections, and without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice in thy judgement, thou ſhalt find in it, no unchriſtian, and unſavory expreſſions, as is reported, contrary to the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of faith, and good manners; but words and phraſes ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only to the furtherance of Loyalty and Chriſtianity, Yet ſuch is the ill fate which doth attend Sermons of this nature, in theſe ſqueamiſh, crazy, and brainſick Times, that, what through inadvertency, or malignancy, they alwayes meet with an ill conſtruction. And ſuch ill fortune hath this poor loyal Sermon unhappily met with; and ſuch hard entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath it received. For ſome chattering Martens, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ill Birds, of an ill brood,
<pb facs="tcp:37758:8"/>(who can ſwallow up Clay, Dirt, and Dung; <hi>viz.</hi> Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Haereſy, Perjury, and all kind of Impiety, to build up their own Neſts; but will not away with any thing of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, Loyalty, and Honeſty, which may tend to the aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of others) have garrulouſly noiſed abroad, that this Sermon was full of untruths, prophaneneſs, and unchriſtian expreſſions, tending rather to the deſtruction, than the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the hearers; and that, the Preacher of it, was full of irreverence in his Prayer, and like a mad man in his Preaching. To wipe away which malevolent and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Aſperſions (not to give them any harſher language) I have been importuned by ſome more judicious and honeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, (though diſſwaded by others) to commit this Sermon to the Preſs, and to commend it to publick view, leaving my ſelf, in point of irreverence in the Pulpit, to the judgement of others that were then preſent, as well as they, and better acquainted with Devotion, and behaviour in it, than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And therefore, good Reader, before thou doſt ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up ſuch injurious and ſcandalous reports, at the ſecond hand, with too much credulity, let me intreat thee, to peruſe this Sermon ſeriouſly, and to weigh the Contents, with the Circumſtances of it, conſiderately; and then, I am confident, upon ſuch mature deliberation, (except thou beeſt infected with the Leaven of <hi>Phanaticiſm,</hi>) thou wilt neither judge the Authour to be mad, nor the Sermon to be unchriſtian, or unlawful.</p>
            <p>We find it recorded in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> that when St. <hi>Paul,</hi> before <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and others, did diſcourſe of his Converſion, and the hope of the Reſurrection, (things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the current of the times then, as loyalty and honeſty amongſt moſt men are now) <hi>Feſtus</hi> the Governour (rightly ſirnamed <hi>Porcius,</hi> from his hoggiſh diſpoſition) ſtood up, and ſaid, with a loud voice, that <hi>Paul</hi> was beſides himſelf, and that too much Learning had made him mad, <hi>Act. 26.24.</hi> I will not ſay I was beſide my ſelf, or the Text, when, before a Reverend Prelate, and ſome Perſons of Honour, as well as thoſe pragmatical Mechanicks, I diſcourſed of our <hi>Sions</hi> Reverſion out of Captivity, by the Kings happy Return into his Kingdoms; and of his Majeſties Reſurrection, in the day of his Nativity. But, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> anſwered <hi>Feſtus,
<pb facs="tcp:37758:9"/>I am not mad, O noble</hi> Feſtus, <hi>but ſpeak the words of truth and ſoberneſs,</hi> Act. <hi>26.25.</hi> So ſhall I reply upon thoſe grunting Cavillers, not Cavaliers, that I was not mad, through too much Learning, (though I may ſafely ſay, there was more Learning in the Sermon, than they that ſpake againſt it, did underſtand) but I did ſpeak the words of truth and ſoberneſs: Yet, I muſt confeſs, not without ſome zeal to the Cauſe I had in hand, and fervency in the delivery of it. But if I were mad, or beſides my ſelf, (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Whether we be beſides our ſelves, it is to God: Or whether we be ſober, it is for your Cauſe, 2 Cor. 5.13.</hi> It was for God, and the King; to inculcate Thankfulneſs to God, and to enforce Loyalty to the King, for the happy return of our unhappy Captivity.</p>
            <p>As for untruths, I know none in it: if thou, good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or any other, can detect, or diſcover any, which as yet are hidden to me, I ſhall readily undergo the penalty to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon falſe Prophets, or Preachers; and thank thee, or them, for better information,</p>
            <p>But, it may be thou wilt ſay, (as is reported) I wiſh'd them all <hi>hang'd;</hi> and that is to curſe; a thing unfitting for a Miniſter; and both unchriſtian, and unlawful.</p>
            <p>Fair and ſoftly, good Reader, not too much of that: I ſaid then, and ſo thou ſhalt find in the Cataſtrophe, and cloſe of the Sermon, that I would conclude all, for that time, with a Votive Acclamation for the King, King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> by whoſe return into his Kingdoms, God was pleaſed to turn our Captivity: And it was the ſame, with ſome alteration, and addition, which was ſometimes aſcribed, by the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> then the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and, in brief, is this: I wiſhed to the King, His Majeſty, <hi>A long Life, a happy Raign, and continual Victory over all his Enemies.</hi> And I hoped then, and ſo do ſtill, that all good Subjects would ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> But for thoſe that were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, and would not ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> I wiſh'd they were <hi>hang'd,</hi> and for Verſe ſake, I ſaid, Agen, Agen: which then I repeated for the greater emphaſis and confirmation of what I had ſaid.</p>
            <p>Now, good Reader, underſtand me aright: I wiſhed the
<pb facs="tcp:37758:9"/>wiſh, and ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to it. But to whom did I wiſh it? It was not to all in general, as is falſly reported; but it was to Rebells, that would not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to my good wiſh for the King; and not to good Subjects, that will concurr with me in my wiſh, and <hi>Amen</hi> it. And I think, till I ſhall be better informed, I might, and yet may ſafely uſe this wiſh.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown to thoſe that have been converſant in the Histories of former times, (that we may not rely upon the judgement, or fancy, of thoſe that are experienced only in the ſullen and ſelf-willed manners of latter dayes) that this, and the like phraſes, have been, and ſtill are Proverbial Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, which, in all Countries, upon ſudden occaſions, have been frequenntly uſed, to expreſs mens abhorrency, and diſlike, to thoſe that have spoken, or done, any thing, contrary to the Law of Nature, and good manners. So you may read in <hi>Ariſtophanes,</hi> that when the <hi>Greeks</hi> of old, would wiſh ill to any man, they uſed this Proverbial Imprecation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Away with him to the Crows!</hi> Which was a place of puniſhment among the <hi>Theſſalians,</hi> where men being put to death, were left as meat for the Crows to devour. And from hence aroſe that adagious ſaying of <hi>Antiſthenes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>'Tis better to fall into the hands of Crows</hi> (if it be not a bull to ſay ſo) <hi>than the hands of Rooks:</hi> He meant Flatterers, and I agree with him: for the Crows devour thoſe only that are dead: but Flatterers and Rooks conſume even thoſe that are alive. Among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> when they would expreſs their hatred, or anger, unto any, they were wont to uſe theſe and the like phraſes: <hi>Ad Furcam;</hi> Or, <hi>in Crucem;</hi> Or, <hi>in rem malam abeat!</hi> Which in plain Engliſh, have no other ſignification, than, <hi>Let him be hang'd!</hi> And the <hi>Italians,</hi> ſtill to this day, (not to mention the uſance of the Grave <hi>Spaniard, Sé<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ahor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cádo;</hi> Or the cuſtom of the Light <hi>French,</hi> whom yet we imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in all other faſhions, <hi>Que y ſoit Pandue;</hi> becauſe I will not ſtand long in enumerating the ſeveral expreſſions of other Nations, upon the like occaſions) are wont to ſay, <hi>Via alle furchè; à Capeſtro; à malo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a;</hi> Or, <hi>à malviaggio,</hi> to whatſoever, or whomſoever doth croſs their humors.</p>
            <p>But not to be ſuch Humoriſts, altogether, to follow the Eccentrick manners of the Heathen, (who yet may riſe up in
<pb facs="tcp:37758:10"/>judgement, and condemn the manners of ſome Chriſtians) or imitate the Exotick cuſtoms of other Nations, that are For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners and Strangers to us, as well as to our Religion, for the Vindication of this imprecation; let us make our addreſs to, and ſearch the holy Scriptures, as our Saviour commands us, <hi>Joh. 5.39.</hi> And ſee, if we cannot warrant, and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, from thoſe ſacred Records, which are the Fountaine of Life, this our wiſh to all Rebells, and Imprecation of death: And ſo, in turning over thoſe holy pages, we ſhall find, without much difficulty of ſearch, expreſſions tending to the ſame ſenſe, though not in the ſame terms. Doth not St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (and I believe you will ſay (if not, he ſaith it himſelf, <hi>1. Cor. 7.40.</hi>) he had the Spirit of God) in a manner uſe the like Imprecation? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be</hi> Anathema Maranatha: that is, <hi>let him be accurſed, 1 Cor. 16.22.</hi> Which Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation of the Apoſtle, is a great deal more, and of a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er nature, than I did wiſh to all Rebells, that love not the King, and will not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to his ſafety. For I wiſh'd them only to be hang'd, a corporal puniſhment; that ſo, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their repentance (if God ſhall be pleaſed to give them the grace, for very few of the Rebells who have been Executed, (as it hath been obſerved, with Chriſtian ſorrow, and hearty grief) have had ſo much remorſe and ſenſe of that horrid ſin, but have died impenitent) <hi>Their Souls may be ſaved,</hi> (to make uſe of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> phraſe) <hi>in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> But St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Imprecation goes further, even to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both of body and ſoul: which I wiſhed not. And this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation of the Apoſtle, you ſhall find, that he doth not only uſe it once, but he doth iterate it again, and again, as I did mine, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> againſt the falſe Prophets that troubled the Church, and endeavoured to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Gospel of Chriſt: <hi>If an Angel from Heaven</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>preach otherwiſe unto you, than that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed. As we ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo ſay I now again: if any man preach unto you otherwiſe than ye have received, let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. <hi>1.8.9.</hi> The word in the Original, in both places, is the ſame with that in the former to the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Let
<pb facs="tcp:37758:10"/>him be accurſed, let him be excommunicated, let him be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and debarred the ſociety of men, as not belonging to the Kingdom of God, but a Son of <hi>Belial,</hi> or Confuſion, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Dominion of Sathan.</p>
            <p>And yet to come nearer to our preſent purpoſe, to our wiſh in hand, which is now in diſpute, and ſo much controverted, <hi>Let them be hang'd!</hi> Do not we read the ſame wiſh in the Old Teſtament? In the Hiſtory of <hi>Samuel,</hi> concerning <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaloms</hi> Rebellion, you may obſerve, when <hi>Cuſhi</hi> brought ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to King <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Abſaloms</hi> death, who had been the Ring-Leader of that great Rebellion which forced King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (as the late Rebellion forced King <hi>Charles,</hi> of happy memory, to flie from <hi>London</hi>) for the ſafeguard of his life; in which Rebellion, by the juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, he was hang'd by the hair of his head, in ſtead of a Halter, (God diſpoſing, or deſigning his hair to perform that office,) between Heaven and Earth, as not worthy to go to Heaven, nor yet fit to live longer upon Earth, for that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Rebellion againſt the King his Father; When <hi>David</hi> enquired concerning him, ſaying, <hi>Is the young man</hi> Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom <hi>ſafe?</hi> His anſwer was, in effect the ſame, that I did wiſh to all Rebells, that will not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the Kings ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as he was: <hi>The Enemies of my Lord the King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and all that riſe againſt thee, to do thee hurt, be as that young man is, 2</hi> Sam. <hi>18.32. Be as that young man is,</hi> how is that? it is, as if he had ſaid, which I did wiſh to ſuch Rebells, <hi>Let them be hang'd!</hi> For <hi>Abſalom,</hi> as you may read before in that ſtory, was hanged in an Oak, <hi>2 Sam. 18.9.</hi> Yea, <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> of whom King <hi>David</hi> gives the character, that he was <hi>a good man</hi> (if any ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept against the others wiſh) <hi>and cometh with good tydings:</hi> Although he did not wiſh all the Rebells hang'd, as <hi>Cuſhi</hi> had done; yet, when he told the King the news, he ſaid, <hi>All is well:</hi> So that he approved it to be well, that <hi>Abſalom</hi> was hanged. <hi>And he fell down</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>to the Earth upon his face, before the King, and ſaid, Bleſſed be the Lord thy God, which hath delivered up the men that lift up their hand againſt my Lord the King, 2 Sam. 18.28.</hi> So that, though he did not wiſh all the Rebels hang'd, as <hi>Cuſhi</hi> did; yet he bleſſed God for delivering them up, that had riſen againſt
<pb facs="tcp:37758:11"/>him, ſome to the Sword, and others to the Gallows. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is a kind of wonder to me, that either good Chriſtians, or loyal Subjects, ſhould ſo much ſpeak againſt that Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which I then wiſhed to all ſuch Rebells, as would not ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> to <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, if notwithſtanding what I have alleged in defence of that wiſh, it ſhould ſtill ſtick in the ſtomacks of ſome, that would be now accounted as good Chriſtians, as formerly they were, in their own account, the greateſt Saints; give me leave, to leave a Pill or two for them, to purge away that choller which they bear to ſuch an Imprecation. For, let me ask of thee, good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is it not lawful, to wiſh that to them, which they, who were the only Saints, themſelves then being Judges, did practiſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others? Is it not lawful to wiſh them <hi>hang'd,</hi> to rid them out of the way, that we be no longer troubled with them, as they did both wiſh to, and deal with us, when time was, and they had the power in their hands? May we not give them a <hi>Rowland,</hi> for their <hi>Oliver?</hi> I ſhall not need to tell you, it is too ſenſibly known, by ſad experience, (as one ſometimes ſaid, <hi>aerumnabilis experientia me docuit;</hi> ſo may we ſay, ſad experience hath taught us) that thoſe kind of men, that will not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the Kings ſafety and proſperity, did both wiſh, and ſpeak, and do all that they could, to hang us that wiſhed well to the King; and to rid us out of the way, that they might not be troubled with us. And therefore, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even by their own Laws, I ſee no reaſon, but we may wiſh, and do the like to them.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, it is not Chriſtian-like, to wiſh, or do evil for evil. What then will you make of them that did ſo much evil to us? Will you deny them to be Chriſtians? They will take it in dudgeon if you do, and ſay they are better Chriſtians than you. Now I will grant you they were Chriſtians: but it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in name only, but not in deed. And I ſhall make it good, that we, who are the Kings friends, though diſpretiated by them, may be Chriſtians, both in name and in deed, although we wiſh the like to them. What think you of St. Paul after his Converſion (for before, according to his own confeſſion, he was a Perſecutor of the Church of God, <hi>Philip. 3.6.</hi> and did breath forth ſlaughter and threatnings againſt the Diſciples, as thoſe Saints did againſt us, <hi>Act. 9.1.</hi>) was he not a Chriſtian? Yet, if you look into his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> you ſhall find, that
<pb facs="tcp:37758:11"/>he uſed the ſame Imprecation that I did, or one to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Doth not he wiſh an <hi>Utinam abſcindantur</hi> to the like ſort of men? <hi>I would to God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they were even cut off that trouble you,</hi> Gal. <hi>5.12. And he that troubleth you, ſhall bear his judgement, whoſoever he be,</hi> V. <hi>10.</hi> Is not this the ſame, in effect, with what I wiſhed? <hi>Would they were hanged;</hi> Or, <hi>Let them be hang'd!</hi> And do not we ſay of thoſe that are <hi>hang'd,</hi> they are <hi>cut off?</hi> It is true, <hi>I would they were cut off,</hi> and <hi>Let them be hang'd,</hi> are not reciprocal: they are not <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini convertibiles,</hi> as the <hi>Logicians</hi> term is, <hi>convertible terms:</hi> Becauſe every one that is <hi>cut off,</hi> is not <hi>hanged:</hi> though every one that is <hi>hang'd,</hi> may be ſaid to be <hi>cut off.</hi> To ſuch therefore, as are implacable Enemies of God, and his Church, and of civil ſociety, yea, and of all mankind, as abdurate and obſtinate Rebells are, who will not be reclaimed, or reduced, to due obedience, though the King ſhew them never ſo much grace and clemency, I think we may ſafely wiſh, without breach of Charity or Chriſtianity, that they may be <hi>hanged,</hi> and <hi>cut off,</hi> that they trouble us no further, as formerly they have done, and would again, if they could, as is too apparent by their practiſes, involve us in another Civil War.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I demand again, whether it be lawful for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>Vim, vi repellere,</hi> to repel, or drive away force by force, to withſtand one power with another? Where yet miſtake me not, as too many of latter dayes have been miſtaken; I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, whether it be lawful for Children to riſe up againſt their Parents, when they do chaſtiſe them; or for Inferiours to riſe up againſt their Superiours, when they do correct them; or for Subjects to riſe up againſt their Princes, when they draw forth the ſword of juſtice for to puniſh them: in all which caſes it is utterly unlawful, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without all contradiction, beyond diſpute. But I do mean, in reſpect of Chriſtians in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, where there is no ſuch relation, as between Parents and Children; between Superiours and Inferiours; between Princes and Subjects; when Chriſtians ſhall aſſault and offer violence to one another; Whether is it lawful to take up Arms againſt Arms, and to repel one force with another to ſave ones ſelf? Shall men unjuſtly take up Arms to cut our throats, and ſhall not we do the like to preſerve our ſelves? It was a queſtion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pounded by <hi>Horace,</hi> to condemn the ſupinity and negligenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> come in his time.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:12"/>
            <q>
               <l>Ut jugulent homines, ſurgunt de nocte latrones:</l>
               <l>Ut teipſum ſerves, non expergiſceris?</l>
            </q>
            <p>And ſhall not we make the ſame Interrogation in this caſe? Shall Theeves riſe up in the night to kill us, and ſhall not we awake to ſave our ſelves? Self-preſervation, as it is a principle innate in every Creature, (for every Creature doth ſeek to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it ſelf by nature;) ſo it was the chief Maxime in requeſt, amongſt thoſe Saints in their Modern Policy, when they had took up Arms to drive away the King, and keep him out. And now the King (God bleſs him, and bleſſed be God for him) is come home, and through Gods ſpecial Providence, come in again into his Kingdoms; is it not lawful to wiſh that ſuch Saints in their own eſteem, but in deed Rebells, as have taken up Arms ſo unjuſtly againſt him; or would take up Arms again as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly againſt him, may be puniſhed with the ſword of juſtice, and cut off? Well then, if we may repel force by force, when we are aſſaulted (otherwiſe, when men come to cut our throats, we muſt ſtand ſtill, and not ſave our ſelves) then it is as lawful to wiſh them <hi>hanged,</hi> and <hi>cut off,</hi> that would, if they could, hang us, or any other way cut us off, and make away with us. They want no will, (as we daily hear by their expreſſions, and ſee by their deſigns and endeavours,) they want only power or opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to effect it.</p>
            <p>And yet for further ſatisfaction in this caſe, I will tell you, that there ought to be a diſtinction, and a difference made in ſuch our Wiſhes, and Imprecations. For we muſt not, nor did I, wiſh all hang'd in general, though I be traduced and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated for ſo doing. Therefore, when at any time we make ſuch an Imprecation, and uſe ſuch a Wiſh, <hi>Let them be hang'd,</hi> we muſt take heed, that we make it, and direct it aright: We muſt make a diſtinction, both of the Cauſes, for which; the Perſons, againſt whom; and the Affections, with which we do wiſh ſuch an Imprecation, that any one be <hi>cut off,</hi> or <hi>hanged.</hi> For St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when, in the forenamed places, he accurſed the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and wiſhed them <hi>cut off,</hi> becauſe they troubled the Church of God, did not wiſh thoſe Imprecations in reſpect of his own cauſe, and as they were his own private enemies; but in reſpect of the cauſe of God, and as they were the publick enemies of his
<pb facs="tcp:37758:12"/>truth. And to ſpeak truly, when I wiſhed thoſe Rebells <hi>hang'd,</hi> that would not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the Kings ſafety and proſperity: I did not uſe that Imprecation, in reſpect of mine own cauſe, or, as they were mine own enemies; but, in reſpect of the cauſe of God, and the King, his Vice-gerent, as they were the publick enemies of both. Then again, we muſt diſtinguiſh in ſuch wiſhes, between the perſons againſt whom ſuch Wiſhes and Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are made. For ſome enemies are placable and curable; as we ſee many of the late Rebells, having ſeen their errours, and been convinced of their folly, have repented, and become good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: And ſuch as theſe, the King, our Father of the Country, hath indulged, and given them a gracious pardon; and the Church, our Mother, hath reſtored them, and received them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her boſome. And others again are implacable, and incurable, of whoſe converſion, and reformation, and ſo ſalvation, there is no hope, or as yet, but very little. As St. <hi>Paul</hi> then did direct his Imprecations againſt thoſe enemies of God, and his Church, which were implacable and incurable; So did I my wiſh, to ſuch Rebells as are implacable and incurable; to ſuch as are rigidly obſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate in their Rebellious courſes, and will not be reclaimed and reformed. And becauſe they will not turn from their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion to their due allegiance, and become good Subjects; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wiſhed they might be turned for their diſobedience, and being Rebells. In the laſt place, we muſt diſtinguiſh likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the affections, with which ſuch Imprecations are made. For ſome are carnal, and, to uſe St. <hi>James</hi> his phraſes, are <hi>earthly, and ſenſual, yea deviliſh, which are not from above, Ja. 3.15.</hi> As raſh anger, hatred, deſire of revenge, and the like. Other affections are more ſpiritual and divine, which deſcend from above, and are heavenly; as a zeal of Gods glory, and of the ſafety of his Curch. Now, as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he wiſhed the falſe Apoſtles were <hi>cut off,</hi> was not carried with a carnal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but with a zeal of Gods glory, and the good of his Church: So, I aſſure you, when I wiſhed all ſuch Rebells <hi>hang'd</hi> as would not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the Kings ſafety and proſperity, I did it not with a meer carnal affection to have them <hi>hang'd;</hi> but with a zeal to Gods glory, the good of his Church, and the peace and welfare of our King and his Kingdoms which have been ſo long diſtracted, and diſquieted, and yet are diſturbed with them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:13"/>
            <p>As for thoſe places, which may be alleged to the contrary; <hi>1.</hi> from St. <hi>Paul: Bleſs them which perſecute you: bleſs, I ſay, and curſe not,</hi> Ro. <hi>12.14. And recompence to no man evil for evil,</hi> Ro. <hi>12.17. And ſee that none render evil for evil unto any man, 1</hi> Theſ. <hi>5.15.</hi> Then <hi>2.</hi> from St. <hi>Peter: Love as brethren; be courteous, not rendring evil for evil, 1</hi> Pet. <hi>3.9.</hi> And <hi>3.</hi> from our Saviour himſelf: <hi>Love your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: bleſs them that curſe you: do good to them that hate you: and pray for them that deſpitefully uſe you, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute you,</hi> Mat. <hi>5.44.</hi> They, and all ſuch like places, muſt be underſtood of our own private and particular enemies, and not of the publick enemies of God, his Church, and truth, as all Rebells are. And therefore to ſuch, if there be any ſuch, as I fear there are too many, that are obdurate and implacable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, ſeeing they are the publick enemies of God, his Church, and of all mankind, we may ſafely wiſh a <hi>Suſpendantur,</hi> as well as King <hi>David,</hi> and other of Gods Servants, have wiſhed a <hi>Confundantur</hi> to the like ſort of men. <hi>So let all thine enemies periſh O Lord!</hi> So ſang <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi> of the enemies of God, in their ſong of thanksgiving, after their victory over <hi>Siſera,</hi> and his Hoſt, <hi>Jud. 5.31. Confundantur! Let them be confounded, and turned back, as many have evil will unto Sion!</hi> So prayeth <hi>David</hi> againſt the enemies of Gods Church, <hi>Pſal. 129.5.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Let them be aſhamed, or confounded, that tranſgreſs without a cauſe!</hi> So wiſheth the ſame Prophet again againſt Rebells, that are the enemies of both, <hi>Pſal. 25.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for us that are Miniſters, becauſe ſome are ſo nice, and make it ſuch a hainous crime, for us to make, or uſe ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, I ſay, being ſeconded with the Authority of as able Divines as ſhall contradict it, that it is more lawful for us; yea, we ought rather than others, to uſe ſuch an Imprecation, and to wiſh ſuch a Wiſh. For we that are Prieſts, who are, in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> language, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſet apart, and ſeparated unto the Goſpel of God,</hi> Ro. <hi>1.1. And to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter about holy things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the general Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Book of Common Prayer.</note> Whoſe Office it is, (as is ſuggeſted) to pray for the people, and to bleſs them, and not to curſe: I ſay, we muſt not only pronounce the bleſſing of Abſolution to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon their true repentance, as is enjoyned us in our Office; but we muſt alſo, it is our duty to denounce the ſentence of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication
<pb facs="tcp:37758:13"/>againſt all ſuch as are obſtinate and impenitent Offendors. And thoſe, whom our Mother the Church will not receive into her boſome here, God our Father, we may aſſure our ſelves, will not receive into his Kingdom hereafter. <hi>Whoſe ſins ſoever ye remit,</hi> ſaith our Saviour to his Apoſtles, <hi>they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: and whoſe ſins ſoever ye retain, they are retained, Joh. 20.23.</hi> So that, what Gods Miniſters, in their ſacred Office, do upon Earth, God himſelf, according to his promiſe, will ratify in Heaven. And we that are Prieſts, his Miniſters, muſt not only give the Benediction, or Bleſſing, to the people; but we muſt alſo, ſometimes, go into the Pulpit,<note place="margin">See the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt Sinners.</note> as you may ſee in the Rubrick, and there read the Commination. We muſt not only go into Mount <hi>Gerizzim,</hi> to pronounce the bleſſing: but we muſt ſometimes go into Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> to denounce a curſe to ſuch as deſerve it, <hi>Deut. 27.12.</hi> Now St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, that there are ſome who are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Curſed Children, 2</hi> Pet. <hi>2.14.</hi> Children to whom the curſe doth of right belong, as well as the bleſſing doth to others: and from theſe we are not to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, but we muſt denounce the curſe unto them. There is an <hi>Eſau</hi> to be hated, as well as a <hi>Jacob</hi> to be loved, <hi>Ro. 9.13.</hi> And there are ſome, <hi>ex ſemine Serpentis,</hi> as well as others, <hi>ex ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Mulieris:</hi> ſome that are of the Serpents brood, as well as of the Womans ſeed: the one to be accurſed; the other to be bleſſed. And therefore, to ſuch as are <hi>Eſaus,</hi> we may ſhew our hatred, as well as our love, to thoſe that are <hi>Jacobs.</hi> And to thoſe of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents brood, as all Rebells are, we may not only, after Gods own example, <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> Our Saviours pattern, <hi>Mat. 23.13.14.</hi> And the Apoſtels doctrine and practice, <hi>Act. 8.20.</hi> &amp; <hi>13.10.</hi> Pronounce a Malediction; but we muſt alſo, we are bound to it; it is part of our Office, to denounce a Curſe to ſuch ſort of men: and I ſee no reaſon, but we may, as others, ſo the curſe of <hi>hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Tree,</hi> Gal. <hi>3.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore (good Reader) to draw to a concluſion, that the Gates, like thoſe of <hi>Myndas,</hi> be not bigger than the City; and the Preface, longer than the Sermon; I muſt tell thee, he that will not ſay, <hi>God ſave the King!</hi> or <hi>Amen</hi> to it, be he what he will and pretend never ſo much, is a Rebell in his heart, though he dares not expreſs ſo much in words, and doth tacitely wiſh the Kings confuſion. He that will not pray for him, prays againſt him: and that is Treaſon adjudged by our Laws. He
<pb facs="tcp:37758:14"/>that denies to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to the Kings ſafety and preſervation, brings himſelf into a Premunirie of wiſhing the Kings ruine &amp; deſtruction. It was the caſe of <hi>Bigthan</hi> &amp; <hi>Tereſh,</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlains of King <hi>Ahaſuerus:</hi> they did not lay hands on the King: but, as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> renders it, <hi>Voluerunt inſurgere;</hi> they had a mind, or a will to kill the King; and for it they were both <hi>hanged</hi> on a Tree, as you may read, <hi>Eſt. 2.21.22.</hi> And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they be, that ſhall make themſelves guilty of Treaſon, by gain-ſaying <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> or denying an <hi>Amen</hi> to the Kings ſafety and proſperity, if they be once brought to the Bar, and arraigned, and convicted of Treaſon, for being Rebells, and denying an <hi>Amen</hi> to His Majeſties ſafety and proſperity, the Judge (as they will find, by ſad experience, as their brethren have done before them) will pronounce from the Bench, that which I did then denounce from the Pulpit, <hi>Suſpendantur! Let them be hang'd!</hi> And ſo I ſhall leave them there, to go with their doom, from thence to the place from whence they came, and from thence to the place of Execution, to receive the reward of their Rebellion and Treaſon: and the Lord have mercy upon their Souls.</p>
            <p>Yet, Candid Reader, <hi>For my Brethren and Companions ſake,</hi> next to the King, the Queen, the Queen-Mother, the Royal Progeny, and thoſe that have been true, and loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and Sufferers in, and for, the Royal Cauſe, <hi>I wiſh thee proſperity: Yea, becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek to do thee good,</hi> Pſal. <hi>122.8.9.</hi> And ſo, good Reader, farewel: and take this <hi>Epiphonema</hi> along with thee,</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>— Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</l>
                  <l>Candidus imperti: Si non, his utere mecum.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> R. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37758:14"/>
            <head>PSAL. 14.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">When the Lord turneth the Captivity of his People, then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be right glad.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the title of this Pſalm be various, according to the various interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Expoſitors: yet the Argument is the ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the judgement of the beſt Commentators. And if you pleaſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your eye, and look further to the 53<hi>d.</hi> Pſalm,<note place="margin">Pſal. 53.</note> you ſhall there perceive the Contents of this, to be the ſame with the Argument of that Pſalm; and both of them to inſinuate, and confirm this truth unto us, That though the Children of God be afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perſecuted, (not only by the Heathen and Infidels, which have no knowlege of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.6.</note> and call not upon his Name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.6. being the wild Boars of the Wood and in the Forreſt without,<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.13.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.13. but alſo by the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ungodly, who profeſs to know God, though they deny him in their works, being the crafty Foxes within, and in the Pale of the Church,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15.) yet their Salvation will undoubtedly come from God, who is thei Saviour and Redeemer,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.14.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.14. And this our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth make good unto us, as in theſe two, ſo in others of his Pſalms; where he both doth comfort the godly in their afflictions, and alſo doth encourage them in all their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37758:15"/>tryals and temptations, ſtill to depend upon God the rock of their ſtrength: For as he aſſures them by his own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, though many, and grievous be the troubles of the righteous; yet, when they cry unto God in their affliction, the Lord heareth them, and delivereth them out of all,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.16.17.</p>
            <p>They both begin and end alike, this fourteenth, and the three and fiftieth Pſalm; though there be ſomething inſerted in the middle of the one, which is omitted in the navel of the other.</p>
            <p>Yet though the Argument, beginning, and ending of both Pſalms, be one and the ſame; the titles of both are various, and differ according to the ſeveral Expoſitions of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and the ſeveral Editions we find them in. I ſhall, with your leave, deſcant a while upon the title of that Pſalm firſt, which in order we meet with laſt. To the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Muſick on <hi>Machalath,</hi> an Inſtructing Pſalm of <hi>David.</hi> So, according to the original, runs the title of the 53 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> Pſalm. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So the <hi>Septuagint</hi> renders it. <hi>In finem pro</hi> Maeleth <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intelligentiae</hi> David: the vulgar tranſlate it. To him that excelleth on <hi>Mahalath,</hi> a Pſalm of <hi>David</hi> to give inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So our Engliſh Bibles have it. But the moſt exact and beſt Tranſlation, commanded and furthered by King <hi>James,</hi> of happy memory, the moſt learned of Kings, and the King of learned men in his time, tranſlated out of the Originals, and compared diligently with former Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſets it forth in this wiſe, as you may read in its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription: <hi>To the chief Muſician upon Mahaleth, Maſchil, a Pſalm of</hi> David.</p>
            <p>Now, according to the difference of the Tranſlations and Editions, the Authors that expound and comment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, do differ likewiſe. For ſome read it, <hi>Ad haeredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Eruditivum</hi> David; Where, by <hi>Davids</hi> eruditive, they would have us to comply with them in our judgements, that this Pſalm was an Erudition, or Revelation of that great, ſignal, and famous calamity, which the Jews ſuffered by the Greeks, under <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes:</hi> at whom, as one moſt impiouſly imperious, proud, and inſolent, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, and that other Pſalm which begins with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37758:15"/>doth point and indigit; and of whom, and his mon outragious, cruel, and ſacrilegious acts, you may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your ſelves, if you dare look into the Apocryphal Books, without any prejudice, in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others imagine that Pſalm to be written Prophetically of the people of the Jews, who were the Aſſaſſines and Murtherers of Chriſt, in putting him to death, who was the Lord of life, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.15.<note place="margin">Acts 3.15.</note> and crucifying him that came to bring Salvation to them.</p>
            <p>Others diſagree in the letter, or matter of the title: and for the word <hi>Ad haereditatem,</hi> or inheritance, ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it, <hi>Ad congregationem,</hi> to the Congregation. Where yet you muſt not underſtand, by Congregation, ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations or Meeting-houſes, as our Phanaticks do now a days frequent, and haunt: for they love no Muſick; they will have no Organs; no Singing and Melody, but what their natural Organs and Pipes can make; all other Muſick is Popiſh and ſuperſtitious with them, becauſe they do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> in loc.</note> But this Pſalm (as St. <hi>Hierom</hi> doth inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it) is directed <hi>ad Chorum,</hi> to a Quire, or company of Singers, where, and with whom, theſe Brethren will in no wiſe keep tune.</p>
            <p>The Chaldee Tranſlation, which to ſome doth ſeem moſt appoſite, reads it thus; <hi>Ad laudandum ſuper ultionem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piorum, qui perturbant haereditatem Domini.</hi> To praiſe God for his vengeance on the wicked, who diſturb and perſecute the Lords inheritance. Which interpretation doth beſt agree with St. <hi>Hieroms</hi> Tranſlation: and in effect is, as if he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Ad Laudandum, ſive ad Chorum, ſive ad Choream ducendam, obvent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum impiorum exitium, quod in hoc Pſalmo praedicitur, eruditio.</hi> An inſtructing Pſalm, to praiſe God, either by Singing, or by Dancing, or by both, for the deſtruction that was to come upon the enemies of God, which is here foretold (and which, Bleſſed be God, by experience we have of late found true) for afflicting and perſecuting the people of God. But however inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters vary in the title, yet as I formerly hinted unto you, all do concurre and agree, even in their diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>greeing, that the Argument is the ſame with that of our Pſalm, and almoſt the very ſame words.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37758:16"/>
            <p>And for the title of our Pſalm, it is as vatious as the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of that: for according to the Hebrew it runneth thus, <hi>To the Maſter of the Muſick, a Pſalm of</hi> David. In the Greek Copies, tranſlated by the ſeventy Interpreters, who were employed by <hi>Ptolomeus Philadelphus,</hi> for the rendring of the Scriptures out of Hebrew into Greek, about the year of the World, according to the computation of ſome Chronologers, 3700. (The ſeveral places deſigned them for that purpoſe, I my ſelf not long ſince have ſeen by St. <hi>Georges</hi> Church, beyond grand <hi>Cairo,</hi> not far from St. <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therines,</hi> where the <hi>Cophti,</hi> or old Chriſtians in <hi>Egypt,</hi> do ſtill meet to worſhip God: and where, if we may give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to tradition (for being under the Turks, they have no Authors that do declare it, but only as it is related among them from one generation to another) they do report, that the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> did lye hid in the time of <hi>Herods</hi> perſecution, when her husband <hi>Joſeph,</hi> admoniſhed by an Angel,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.</note> was forced to flye into <hi>Egypt</hi> with her, and her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Babe, to preſerve him from <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty) I ſay in the Greek Copies we read it inſcribed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which the vulgar tranſlation follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, doth exhibit it thus, <hi>In finem Pſalmus</hi> David. In our more antient Bibles, Printed in <hi>Q. Elizabeths</hi> time, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1589. it is inſcribed, To him that excelleth, a Pſalm of <hi>David:</hi> but King <hi>James</hi> his Verſion gives it in this manner, <hi>To the chief Mufician, a Pſalm of</hi> David.</p>
            <p>It will not be amiſs to conſider them both together: and ſo we ſhall the better learn,<note place="margin">The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Muſick, who?</note> what inſtruction will accrue unto us from this inſtructing Pſalm of <hi>David. To the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Muſick, on Machalath, an inſtructing Pſalm of</hi> David.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ainſworth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ainſworth</hi> Annot. in 4 Pſal.</note> in his Annotations upon the 4th. Pſalm, gives us to underſtand who this Maſter of Muſick was. <hi>To the Maſter of the Muſick</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is to the Overſeer, or to him that excelleth.</hi> The <hi>Chaldee</hi> tranſlateth it to ſing: ſo that we muſt apprehend it in this wiſe or manner: <hi>To him,</hi> that is, <hi>to the Overſeer: or, To him that excelleth in ſinging, a Pſalm of</hi> David. The word <hi>Menatſeach,</hi> in the Original, ſignifieth properly one that urgeth and promoteth the continuance of a thing to the end; or the going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37758:16"/>with a work till it be overcome, or is finiſhed: as you may read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.12, 13. And <hi>Ezra</hi> 3.8, 9.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 34.12, 13. Ezia 3.8, 9.</note> And ſuch men, as in the fore-cited place are called <hi>Menat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchim,</hi> Maſters; in another place are called <hi>Rodim,</hi> Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.16.<note place="margin">1 Kings 5.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now you muſt know, that in Muſick there were Levites appointed for ſeveral duties, as you may ſee 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12. Of which ſome were, <hi>Kvatſeach,</hi> to ply,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 15.12.</note> or ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and be over the reſt: and theſe were ſuch as excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the art of ſinging, and playing on Inſtruments, to whom ſuch Pſalms are intituled, that, by their care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, they might be ſung excellently to the end.</p>
            <p>Which Title of Maſter, thus explained, give us as Schollars to learn this leſſon; That in the Worſhip,<note place="margin">In the Worſhip of God we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end.</note> and Service of God, we ought to continue to the end. It is not ſufficient to come and preſent our ſelves to a piece of Gods Service, and to a piece of a Sermon, and then go away: as the cuſtom of many men (too many now a days) is, to come and peep into a Church, with their Hats on their Heads (an unmannerly cuſtom) as into a Playhouſe; and then having heard a piece of the Service, or a piece of the Sermon, go away, and ſo go to another Church, and do the like; which yet they will not do at a Playhouſe: for there they will ſtay till the Cataſtrophe, or laſt Act be finiſhed, and the Epilogue pronounced. No, it is no acceptable ſervice with God, either to hear a piece of the Service, or to hear a piece of the Sermon, and perform the reſt of his Ordinances by piece-meals; but as we muſt come to the beginning of Gods Service, ſo we are bound to continue till the end of it. And if we look back into Antiquity, we ſhall find, that the Chriſtians in former times, as they were aſhamed, if they did not come to the beginning of Service; ſo they were blamed, if they did not ſtay to the end of it.<note place="margin">Inſtit. 3. C. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Caſſian</hi> tells us (<hi>Instit.</hi> 3. <hi>C.</hi> 7.) that in the antient times of the Church, he that did not come to Prayers, <hi>Priuſquam Pſalmus coeptus finiretur,</hi> before the firſt Pſalm was ended, he did not dare to enter into the Houſe of Prayer; but ſtanding at the door until the reſt came out, <hi>Submiſſâ in terram poenitentiâ, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiae ſuae, vel tarditatis, impetrabat veniam,</hi> by a ſubmiſſive
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37758:17"/>repentance, down to the earth, he obtained pardon for his careleſſneſs and negligence. And for thoſe that were too forward to go from Gods Houſe, before Service was ended, divers of the antient Councils have ſet down Cenſures,<note place="margin">Concil. <hi>Agathen:</hi> Can. 47.</note> as may be ſeen in the Council of <hi>Agatha</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> So that we ſee, we muſt not come to Gods Houſe, and celebrate his Ordinances in a careleſs and perfunctory manner; but we muſt come with the firſt, and ſtay with the laſt; we muſt religiouſly give ear, and hear the whole Service out; and we muſt Chriſtianly attend, and hear the whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon our; and we muſt piouſly wait upon all other holy Adminiſtrations, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even to the end of them; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Biſhop, or Prieſt, ſhall give his diſmiſſion with a Benediction. Which among the Greeks was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the licentiating, or giving leave for the people to be gone. And among the Latines it was termed <hi>Miſſa eſt</hi> (not as the Romaniſts now term their Service, <hi>Miſſa,</hi> the <hi>Maſs,</hi> as fondly, as they perform their Service ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly; but <hi>Miſſa eſt</hi>) <hi>ite, ilicet,</hi> i. e. <hi>ire licet ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo;</hi> There is leave to depart, you may be gone out of the Temple, there is a diſmiſſion: And this was wont to be proclaimed by the Deacon to the <hi>Catechumeniſts, Energu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniſts,</hi> and <hi>Penitentiaries,</hi> who were not admitted to be preſent when the Prieſt was celebrating the holy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. For the Chriſtians in the Primitive times were ſo zealous of the Prieſts, or Biſhops bleſſing, as that they would not depart without it; they thought themſelves, as it were, accurſed, if they had it not. So contrary was the opinion and practice of the Chriſtians, in the infancy of the Church, to that of the new il-luminated Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, in theſe exulcerated times, who are ſo far from being zealous and deſirous of the bleſſing of the Biſhop, or Prieſt, as that they care neither for the Prieſt, nor his Benediction; but abominate both, as they do the name of a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>But here I could relate a ſtory, not impertinent to the purpoſe, of a reverend Divine of this Kingdom; one, whom in my younger years, I had the honour to have more than ordinary acquaintance with; and I was the more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of his acquaintance, becauſe he had the honour to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37758:17"/>be eſteemed the greateſt Scholar, and moſt famous Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, at that time, in, and about thoſe places where he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Norfolk.</hi> This Gentleman being deſired to Preach at St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Church in <hi>Great-Yermouth,</hi> did condeſcend to gratifie the requeſt of thoſe Friends that did invite him; where having finiſhed his Sermon, and going to his after Prayer, for a bleſſing upon what he had delivered, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the people to go out of the Church, eſpecially Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who went home before to prepare their Maſters and Miſtreſſes Dinners againſt they came home, a thing accuſtomary in that place; whereupon he called them back again, and deſired them to take a ſhort ſtory along with them: who coming into the Church again, as faſt as they were going our, after a ſmall pauſe he thus beſpeaks them. <hi>Friends, I have lived your Neighbour theſe</hi> 39. <hi>years, within very few miles of this place, and never before this time yet preached among you; and, except you amend your manners, I ſhall never deſire to preach here again. But the occaſion why I called you back again, is, to let you underſtand, that our Saviour Chriſt, as you may read in the Evangeliſts, had Twelve Apoſtles; and, at the institution of the holy Supper, one of them went away before our Saviour gave the bleſſing, and, Sathan having entred into him, he went and hang'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; I pray God ſend you better fortune! and that you may ſo have, I pray ſtay and take the bleſſing along with you.</hi> The ſtory was ſhort, but it was a ſharp reprehenſion of their ſupine neglect, or willful refuſal to ſtay, and take the Prieſts benediction with them; which though it be ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome Fanaticks, yet it is of great conſequence, and every good Chriſtian will ſtay for it, as their farewel out of Gods Houſe, and a means of their better progreſs to their own.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument <hi>Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath,</hi> what?</note>But proceed we from the Maſter of the Muſick to the Inſtrument, <hi>Machalath,</hi> to ſee what muſick it will make, it being inſcribed in the Title; for of it we ſhall have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſpeak more hereafter, when we come to <hi>Sions</hi> Exulation. And for our better ſatisfaction in this, we muſt take notice, that <hi>Machalath</hi> (as our Anthours do inform us) was a kind of Inſtrument with which they were wont to play when they ſung this Pſalm, not much
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37758:18"/>unlike to <hi>Nechiloth,</hi> which by the name ſeemed to be a kind of wind Inſtruments, as Fluits, Trumpets, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and the like; As <hi>Neginoth</hi> were ſtringed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Muſick, played on with the hand, as the Harp, and the Lute, and the Inſtrument of Ten Strings, of which we read, and with which the righteous are excited, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to praiſe the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.2, 3.</p>
            <p>So that, according to all Editions, the Inſcriptions, or Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of theſe two Pſalms, do teach us to make muſick, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, and being glad, for the vengeance of God ſhewed upon the wicked, who have troubled Gods people, and vexed his inheritance. And that we ought to celebrate ſuch our joy with all kinds of Muſick, both Vocal and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al, with ſtill and loud Muſick, in ſinging and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth our praiſes to God, with joyful and thankful hearts and voices, for the deſtruction of the Enemies of his people and truth. Which, as it is the purport of both our Pſalms we are now treating of; ſo it was the occaſion of our late Solemnitie, the Lord having turned the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of us his people in <hi>England,</hi> by returning our dread Soveraign, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to the native right and inheritance of his three Crowns of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> without the further effuſion of his Subjects blood, ſo much feared, and deſerved, in theſe three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>In the next place, we are to enquire why it is called an <hi>Inſtructing Pſalm of</hi> David, or <hi>Maſchil.</hi> Now the reaſon why it is thus ſtiled,<note place="margin">An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing Pſalm, why?</note> is from the uſe of it: becauſe this, and other Pſalms, that are intituled <hi>Inſtructing Pſalms,</hi> are ſo called, becauſe they give Inſtruction. Even as the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of his Son King <hi>Solomon</hi> are ſaid to give Wiſdom, and Inſtruction, and Underſtanding; becauſe they make men Prudent, and Wiſe, and give Underſtanding, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.2. And this our Prophet doth confirm unto us in the 32 d. Pſalm,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.2.</note> which is alſo intituled, an <hi>Inſtructing Pſalm of</hi> David, a Pſalm that maketh Prudent, that cauſeth Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: as he explains himſelf in the 8 th. verſe of that Pſalm, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So the <hi>Septuagint</hi> do render the words,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.8.</note> 
               <hi>I will wake thee prudent, and inſtruct thee; I will teach thee in the way which thou ſhalt go.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we may obſerve, that the good man <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37758:18"/>(practizing that counſel, which his Son, according to the fleſh, and our Saviour,<note place="margin">Luk, 22.32.</note> gives to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Et tu converſus confirma fratres,</hi> Thou being convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtrenghen thy brethren, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32.) promiſeth to make the reſt of Gods Children partakers of the benefits which he felt, and that (which every Chriſtian ought to do, eſpecially Miniſters, Fathers, and Maſters of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies) he will diligently look, and take care to direct them in the way of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Now a Pſalm (that we may not leave any thing unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, ſince we have begun to unfold the Title) is called in the Hebrew, <hi>Mizmor,</hi> which hath the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of pruning, or cutting off ſuperfluous Twiggs and Branches; and is applyed to Songs, which are compoſed of ſhort Sentences, or Verſes, where many ſuperfluous words are cut off, and taken away. And here, for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter information, that you may the more diſtinctly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what a Pſalm is, it will not be amiſs, to give you to underſtand, that there be three kinds of Songs, which are mentioned in the Pſalmographie of the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.1.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>In Hebrew</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mizmor,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tehillah,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shir.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In Greek</head>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In Engliſh</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hymn,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Song.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>All which three kinds of Songs, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Doctor of the Gentiles, as well as the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> the great Poet of the Jews, doth mention in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> where he exhorts them, and in them all Chriſtians, to be filled with the Spirit, rather than with exceſs of Wine; and to ſpeak to themſelves in Pſalms,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.18, 19.</note> and Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs, making melody in their hearts to the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.18, 19.</p>
            <p>This Song here you ſee it is a Pſalm, the firſt of the three kinds of Songs; and the <hi>Septuagint</hi> read it, as I told you before, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The vulgar Tranſlation among the Latines, <hi>In finem Pſalmus</hi> David, or, <hi>In finem pro Maeleth, intelligentiae</hi> David: A Pſalm of <hi>David</hi> to the end; or for <hi>Maeleth,</hi> an Inſtructing Pſalm of <hi>David</hi> to the end. Which, as I inſinuated above, doth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37758:19"/>leſſon to us, to perſevere and continue in Gods Service to the end; not only whiles we are in the Temple, or Gods Houſe, to continue there till the end of all thoſe holy My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and Diſpenſations be performed, that ſo we may have Gods bleſſing, by the Biſhop, or Prieſt, pronounced upon us; but alſo when we are out of the Temple, in our own houſes, or elſe where; we being, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles us,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.16.</note> Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. We ought to continue in Gods ſervice the whole courſe of our life; ſerving him as good old <hi>Zachary</hi> doth preſcribe unto us in his <hi>Benedictus,</hi> in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the dayes of our life: As the end for which he did redeem us, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74.75.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.74.75.</note> And as we our ſelves did promiſe, to perform faithfully, by our Sureties that did undertake for us, at our Baptiſme, when we were initiated into Chriſts Church, to become Chriſtians, that we might be ſanctified. For then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rubrick</hi> in the Miniſtrat. of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</note> if we do well remember, as we ought, and as our Catechiſm doth rightly inform us, they did promiſe for us, that we would forſake the Devil, and all his works, and conſtantly believe Gods holy Word, and obediently keep his Commandements. And then did we receive the ſign of the Croſs (if we did receive it at all, and the more to be blamed they that do omit it in Baptiſm, becauſe it is ſo ſignificant to put us in mind of our duty) in token, that hereafter we would not be aſhamed to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified, but manfully fight under his Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, againſt Sin, the World, and the Devil, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Chriſts faithful Souldiers and Servants to our lives end.</p>
            <p>But leaving the Title (which yet,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> to uſe St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſaying, is <hi>clavis Pſalmi,</hi> the Key to unlock the meaning of the Pſalm) let us addreſs our ſelves to the Argument of it; which, according to the Dictates of Expoſitors, in brief is this. The holy man David, by the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy, contemplating the conſtitution of the viſible Church; and ſeeing the greater part of the people to lye in their natural eſtate of corruption, working iniquity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety with greedineſs, and hating the Children of God, which are got out of that eſtate by Regeneration,<note place="margin">Philip. 3.6.</note> with a perfect hatred, and perſecuting them with a fiery zeal,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37758:19"/>even to the death, becauſe they will not continue in the ſame exceſs of licentiouſneſs and wickedneſs with them; He both comforts the people of God, that are renewed in the ſpirit of their minds, by minding them, that God doth take care of them, and plead their cauſe againſt the Ungodly for them, in the beginning of the Pſalm; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages them ſtill to perſevere in the wayes of piety and uprightneſs, notwithſtanding their great affliction, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, by giving them hopes of better dayes, in the latter end of the Pſalm; when as by grievous plagues and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted on their Enemies, Chriſt, the Captain of our ſalvation, the Son of righteouſneſs like the Sun coming out of a Cloud, ſhould appear, and manifeſt himſelf unto them, with healing in his wings, <hi>Malach.</hi> 4.2.<note place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So that in ſhort, theſe 2. things, 1. The Deliverance of Gods Church and People. And 2. The Confuſion and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their Enemies, are the Sum and Argument, as of this, ſo of the 53. Pſalm following.</p>
            <p>And indeed, if we ſeriouſly peruſe the holy Scriptures, with an imperfunctory eye, with an eye not negligently diſpoſed, we ſhall obſerve, that theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The final Deliverance of Gods people from the hands of their Enemies (though they be for a while in diſtreſs and captivity under them) which in the beginning of my Text is prayed for. And</item>
               <item>2. The final Deſtruction and Confuſion of Gods and his Peoples Enemies (though they be for a while exalted, and in power over them) which is here fore prophecied in the latter end of my Text; are the ſum and ſubſtance, as of theſe two, ſo of many others in the Book of the Pſalms: Yea the whole ſtory of the Scriptures, if you will take the pains to revolve them your ſelves, or believe the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Divines, who have read them over, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented upon them, is, as you ſhall find, nothing elſe but a Calender of them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In theſe you ſhall read,
<list>
                  <item>1. That the Lord of Hoſts,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.9.24.</note> the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is <hi>El-Nekamoth,</hi> a God of Vengeance againſt his Enemies, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.35.</item>
                  <item>And 2.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.35.</note> That the ſame God, the God of Peace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.<note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
A Letter but changed, is <hi>El-Nechamoth,</hi> a God of Comfort to his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37758:20"/>People,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. And as he is ſerved and pleaſed by men; ſo his Creatures alſo, they are ready to ſerve and pleaſe him, both for the defence of his people, and the offence of thoſe that hate them. So you ſhall find in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> that the Cherubims hold a flaming Sword in their hand to repreſs Gods Enemies,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. And yet they have their wings ſpread abroad to relieve, ſhadow, and ſuccour his Friends,<note place="margin">Ezek. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.11. In <hi>Exodus</hi> you may read likewiſe, that the Cloud was a miſt of darkneſs to confound the <hi>Egyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 13.21.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21. And the ſame Cloud was a pillar of fire to give light and conduct to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 22.</note> 
               <hi>V.</hi> 22. And in the ſame Book, at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the water from beneath, was a gulf to ſwallow up, and drown <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his Hoſt, that did purſue them,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.28. And yet the ſame water was a wall of defence to Gods people, on their right hand, and on their left, to give them ſafe paſſage towards the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.29. So during their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity in <hi>Babylon</hi> (to omit many other inſtances, which might be induced for confirmation, both before their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and whilſt they were in poſſeſſion of the promiſed Land) you may obſerve, that the fiery Furnace which was heated ſeven times more than ordinary, it was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, as it were, to the 3. Children, the ſervants of God, that were caſt bound into it, becauſe they would not obey <hi>Nebuchadnezzers</hi> Decree, againſt Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.22.<note place="margin">Dan. 3.22.</note> And the ſame Furnace became a <hi>Gehenna,</hi> or place of Torment to their Enemies, that threw them into it,<note place="margin">V. 25.</note> 
               <hi>V.</hi> 25. Obſerve it where you will, and you ſhall find ſtill, that theſe two, the Deliverance of Gods People, and the Deſtruction of their Enemies, go ſtill together, for the moſt part, not only in moſt of the Pſalms, but, to ſpeak truth, in moſt part of the Scripture. And as they ſtill go together, ſo you may take notice likewiſe, that though ſometimes they be intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet they alwayes end in the ſafeguard of the Church: which is here both prayed for, and fore-prophecied alſo, in my Text. This is the Concluſion of all Prophecies, of all Judgements, of all Miracles, paſt or preſent, new or old: this is the Sum, and the Cataſtrophe of them.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37758:20"/>
            <p>And ſo I paſs from the outward Court, as it were, of the Title and Argument of the Pſalm, in general, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the inner Temple, and treat of the words of my Text in particular. <hi>Quis dabit?</hi> Or, <hi>Oh ſi quis det!</hi> Who will give Salvation? Or, Oh that Salvation were given unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion!</hi> Oh that the Lord would turn the Captivity of his people! <hi>When the Lord turneth the Captivity of his People, then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be right glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words may be read, apprehended, and treated of three ſeveral wayes, according to the judgement of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors.</p>
            <p>Either
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Hiſtorically,</hi> and according to the Letter,</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Myſtically,</hi> and according to the Figure,</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Analogically,</hi> and according to the uſe we may make of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, If we read them <hi>Hiſtorically,</hi> and according to the Letter, It is true,<note place="margin">1. Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically.</note> that the Deliverance of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the time of King <hi>Saul,</hi> by bringing <hi>David</hi> (that was appointed by God to be King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.14.</note> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. And annointed by <hi>Samuel,</hi> according to Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.13.</note> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.13.) to the Kingdom, was worthy to be wiſhed for, and that with ardency and zeal of affection: becauſe good Princes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the raign of Tyrants, is like the Sun in a comfortable ſhine, after the tedious darkneſs, and dark irkſomeneſs of a great ſtorm. But this is not all which the Text doth aim at, and imply: and therefore in the next place,</item>
               <item>Secondly, We muſt read the words <hi>Myſtically,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</note> and according to the Figure, looking to the ſubſtance, of which this Hiſtory was but a Type; which is in Chriſt, the Son of <hi>David,</hi> according to the fleſh, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſtile him, <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.3. In whom this wiſh,<note place="margin">Ro. 1.3.</note> or prayer hath its accompliſhment. Which, in effect, is this: <hi>Oh that Chriſt, the Saviour of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>were come out of</hi> Sion! And it is the ſame with the ardent deſires of the people of God, in the 53. Pſalm, which concludes in the ſame tenou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.36. <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> in loc.</hi>
                  </note> and with the very ſame words. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37758:21"/>for ſo the <hi>Septuagint</hi> render the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal in that form. Who will give Salvation to <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion?</hi> or, Oh that Salvation were given unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion!</hi> Where in the Original, as the learned in that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage obſerve; the expreſſion is ſet down Salvations, in the Plural Number, to intimate unto us full Salvation, Health, or Deliverance; even the perfection of Salvation, which cometh only by Chriſt, who was to come out of <hi>Sion,</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the praediction of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.20.</note> c. 59.20. <hi>The Redeemer ſhall come out of</hi> Sion, <hi>and ſhall turn away ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity from</hi> Jacob.) and at whom, the form of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> wiſhing here doth look, as to the perſon which ſhould then, and ſhall ſtill give perfect Salvation, and Deliverance to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> even the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16.</item>
               <item>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gically.</note> we may read the words <hi>Analogically,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively, according to the uſe we may make of them, in reſpect of the Churches of God which now are, larely have been, and hereafter may be in Perſecution and Captivity, by the enemies of God and his Truth. In which relation this option or wiſh, here in my Text, hath its place: and there is no good Chriſtian but, in ſuch a caſe, will with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> and the Church of God here in my Text, wiſh, ſigh, breath out, and ingeminate an <hi>Oh ſi quis det!</hi> Oh that Salvation were given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion!</hi> Oh that the Lord would turn the captivity of his people! <hi>When the Lord turneth the Captivity of his people, then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be right glad.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall not inſiſt on the words litterally: the Hiſtory was fulfilled, when after <hi>Sauls</hi> death, <hi>David,</hi> that had been appointed and annointed by God, was now conſtituted and annointed by all the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi> King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.3.</note> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.3. and did deliver the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the hands of all their enemies that did vex and afflict them.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall I preſume to treat of them <hi>Myſtically,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this bringing back the captivity of Gods people the Jews, here propheſied to be under the Goſpel, ſhall be by looſing their captivity corporally, as well as ſpiritually: or whether the Jews ſhall return again to their own Land, or no: Theſe are too deep myſteries for my ſhallow capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37758:21"/>to diue into: although, ſince our late diſtracted times, many more curious than wiſe, and more wiſe than ſobriety would permit them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>al.</hi> Ep.</note> (according to that Proverbial <hi>quippe</hi> of the Epigrammatiſt, <hi>Et qui plus juſto non ſapit, ille ſapit,</hi>) have gone ſo far in their ſpeculations, as to fore-ſee and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, the time when, and the perſons by whom, (and yet I muſt tell you they have groſly erred in their calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and expectation, becauſe we have viſibly ſeen the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary by experience) the Jews, which are now ſo rife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, ſhall be reſtored to their priſtine eſtate, and to the Land of their Nativity; from whence, for putting to death the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and Redeemer of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they have been juſtly ſcattered and diſperſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore I ſhall more modeſtly and ſafely ſpeak of them in the third acception of the words, <hi>Analogically,</hi> as they may be underſtood in relation to the Churches of God, which have been, now are, or hereafter may be under per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and in captivity by the enemies of God and his Truth. And in this conſideration, if we apprehend the words, we ſhall find in the Verſe two generals,
<list>
                  <item>The Churches
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Hoſannah.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Or, The Churches
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Praiſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, There is the Churches <hi>Hoſannah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</note> or Prayer to God for her deliverance, being in captivity. And here we cannot but take notice of <hi>Sions</hi> humiliation.</item>
               <item>Secondly, There is the Churches <hi>Hallelujah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah.</note> or Praiſe to God for being delivered out of captivity. And here we muſt take notice likewiſe of <hi>Sions</hi> exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Church begins with <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> and ſhe ends with <hi>Hallelujah:</hi> and ſo muſt we, if we will approve our ſelves to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the true and genuine Sons of the Church. We muſt begin with <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> and we muſt end with <hi>Hallelujah:</hi> as in this, ſo in all other actions and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings. We muſt pray unto God for deliverance when we are in trouble, and for other bleſſings to be obtained; and we muſt give praiſe unto God for deliverance out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37758:22"/>trouble, and for other bleſſings when obtained, or but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. So the Church doth here: She prays unto God, being in perſecution and in captivity, to turn her captivity, and to give deliverance to his people out of captivity: And ſhe gives praiſe unto God being delivered out of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for turning the captivity of his people, although but promiſed.</p>
            <p>The Churches <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> or Prayer to God for deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance out of captivity, we have in theſe words, <hi>Quis dabit?</hi> or, <hi>Oh ſi quis det!</hi> Who will give? or, Oh that Salvation were given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion!</hi> Oh that the Lord would turn the captivity of his people!</p>
            <p>The Churches <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> or praiſe unto God for her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of captivity, we have in the words following, <hi>Cùm averterit Dominus captivitatem plebis ſuae;</hi> When the Lord turneth the captivity of his people, then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be right glad.</p>
            <p>But if you pleaſe that we ſhould deſcend into a more particular <hi>Analyſis,</hi> or reſolution of the words, we may obſerve in them,<note place="margin">Quadriga copicorum.</note> 
               <hi>Quadrigam Topicorum;</hi> A four-wheeled Charriot of Topicks, by which we ſhall drive on our future exercitation, for the better performance of our enſuing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. There is,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Curioſa interrogatio, Quis dabit?</hi> who will give?</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Pathetica poſtulatio, Oh ſi quis det!</hi> Oh that Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were given!</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Certa determinatio, Reducente</hi> Jehovah; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When the Lord turneth the captivity of his people.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Grata exultatio, Exultabit</hi> Jacob; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be right glad.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Curioſa Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note>Firſt, There is a curious interrogation; <hi>Quis dabit?</hi> Who will give? or, who ſhall give Salvation unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion? Qui curioſe interrogat perplexus nimis eſt,</hi> He that is curious in his interrogations, is very dubious, and ſo the more deſirous of ſatisfaction. <hi>Interrogatio eſt quaſi iterogatio,</hi> (ſaith the Etymologiſt) <hi>quaſi iterum rogatio;</hi> as it were, an asking the ſecond time, again and again. And ſo it teacheth us, when we are in captivity, or any other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37758:22"/>Affliction or trouble, <hi>iterare preces,</hi> to iterate our prayers, &amp; to ingeminate our requeſts; not only <hi>ingemiſcere,</hi> to groan, and ſigh forth our deſires and petitions; but alſo <hi>ingemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> to double our prayers; to iterate our deſires, again and again, till we be delivered.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca poſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note>Secondly, There is a Pathetical poſtulation; or, a moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate wiſh, or ardent deſire: <hi>Oh ſi quis det!</hi> Oh that Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation were given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Sion!</hi> Oh that it were! Would to God it were! <hi>Quis tribuat?</hi> Oh that ſome good body would give it! Such like pathetical expreſſions of the Prophet we meet with alſo in other places: as, <hi>Oh ſi quis efficiat ut fruamur bono!</hi> Who will ſhew us any good?<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.7. And, <hi>Oh ſi quis daret mihi aquam!</hi> Oh that one would give me to drink of the water of the Well of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> which is by the gate! 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.15. <hi>Qui patheticè rogat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.15.</note> 
                  <hi>ardenter poſtulat;</hi> He that asks pathetically, and with affection to a thing, deſireth ardently.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Certa determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note>Thirdly, There is a certain determination, or a moſt aſſured and infallible concluſion; <hi>Reducente</hi> Jehovah <hi>redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem populi ſui turmam;</hi> When the Lord turneth the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of his people; that is, aſſuredly the Lord will turn the captivity of his people. Which is a gracious anſwer to the <hi>Quis dabit?</hi> or, <hi>Oh ſi quis det!</hi> Who will give? or,<note place="margin">Tremelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> Oh that Salvation were given! For, as ſure as Gods people are in captivity; ſo ſure the Lord will turn their captivity, and deliver them out of captivity. Yet if you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this expoſition, becauſe you may think it to be mine own, take Gods own Word for it, who is truth it ſelf,<note place="margin">Joh. 14.6.</note> and cannot lye, or deny his own Word which he hath ſpoken, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> And this you ſhall find in the Prophecy of <hi>Jeremiah. Thus ſaith the Lord, Behold I will bring again the captivity of</hi> Jacobs <hi>Tents, and have mercy on his dwelling places. Jer.</hi> 30.18. and ſo forward, as you may ſee in that,<note place="margin">Jer. 30.18. and 31.</note> and in the following Chapter, where God promiſeth the reſtauration of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Now you muſt know, that <hi>Dei di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, eſt Dei facere;</hi> Gods Word is his Deed. What God ſpeaks, if it be not yet, it is, as if it were done. <hi>Ipſe dixit, &amp; facta ſunt omnia, Gen.</hi> 1. He ſpake the word,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> and all things were created: and what he ſpeaks now, cannot like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but be performed.</item>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37758:23"/>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Grata Exultatio.</note>Laſtly, There is a grateful exultation, or a joyful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulation for ſo great a mercy, as the turning the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Gods people. <hi>Exultabit</hi> Jacob, <hi>&amp; laetabitur</hi> Iſrael; <hi>Then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be right glad.</hi> It is but prophecied in my Text; but we have heard it to be fulfilled in all places; yea, and we ſee it verified every where by experience; <hi>Solutâ captivitate, laeti ſunt cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivi.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>When men are in Priſon, they are heavy and ſad:</l>
                     <l>But when they are free, they are merry and glad.</l>
                  </q>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>So then, as from <hi>Eden,</hi> (of which you may read in the Book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.10.</note>) there went a River to water the Garden, which God had planted; and from thence it was parted and became into four heads, <hi>Gen,</hi> 2.10. In like manner, from this Text,<note place="margin">4 <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
               </note> thus as you ſee I have Analyſed it, there flow four Rivolets of Corollaries, or Doctrinal concluſions, to water the Gardens of our hearts, that, like <hi>Eden,</hi> they may be fruitful both in inſtruction and action, according to godlineſs: that the man of God, which is content to be governed by the Word of God, may be fruitful, and made perfect unto all good works;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, to the ſame purpoſe, in his Epiſtle to his adopted Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> nay his own Son in the faith:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.2.</note> for ſo he ſtiles him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>The firſt Corollary,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </note> or Doctrinal concluſion, which preſents it ſelf from the words of the Text, is this: That God doth ſometimes ſuffer his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his own people, to go into captivity.<note place="margin">God doth ſuffer his <hi>Iſrael</hi> to go into captivity.</note> For here, by <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is meant the people of God: which is made manifeſt by the words next follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or underſtood: Oh that the Lord would deliver his people out of captivity! and, when the Lord turneth the captivity of his people. Now if <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods people, were not in captivity, why do they ſo ardently wiſh and pray to be delivered out of it? Their deſire to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, doth imply that they were in captivity. Thats the firſt concluſion, God doth ſuffer his <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſometimes to go into captivity.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </note> another Corollary, that ariſes from the Text, exhibits it ſelf thus: That it is the duty of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of Gods
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37758:23"/>people, when they are in captivity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> in captivity muſt pray for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</note> to pray for deliverance out of captivity. <hi>Oh ſi reducat Dominus!</hi> Oh that the Lord would deliver his people out of captivity! And for my part, they that are in Priſon, and in Captivity, and will not pray, or deſire to come out of it, let them ſtay there ſtill. We have an old Proverb frequent amongſt us; <hi>He that is in a Ditch, and will not uſe the means to come out, let him lye there ſtill.</hi> And I make this application of it: If a man be in Priſon, Captivity, or any other affliction or ſorrow, and doth not deſire to come out of it; if he will not pray to God for deliverance, let him ſtill continue in it. <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti non fit injuria;</hi> God ſend them ſorrow that love it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Upon <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er God doth turn their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</note>Thirdly, The Corollary or Concluſion, which ariſes from the determination, is an irrefragable poſition, which is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without all controverſy, ſeconded by the teſtimonies, and made good by the examples of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo beyond all contradiction. That upon the prayers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of Gods People, when they are in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and in captivity, the Lord will undoubtedly deliver his people, and turn their captivity. The Participle is of the Preſent Tenſe, <hi>Reducente</hi> Jehovah, <hi>reducem populi ſui tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam;</hi> The Lord turning the captivity of his people: which preſents unto us the certainity of it; as if it were already preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Iſrael</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of captivity, ought to rejoyce and be glad for it.</note>Then, in the laſt place, the fourth Corollary doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the neceſſity of Praiſe, as the ſecond did infer the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Prayer: That, when God, upon the Prayers of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> his People, ſhall have turned their captivity and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them from the hands of their enemies, under whom they were captives, they ought, by way of gratitude, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their thankfulneſs for ſuch a mercy, and to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their deliverance, by being joyful and glad.</p>
            <p>Theſe are, as it were, the four Wheels of our Topical Charriot, by which, as formerly I hinted unto you,<note place="margin">Biga in Hoſannch.</note> we ſhall drive on our future diſcourſe. Two whereof belong to the <hi>Hoſannah</hi> (in <hi>Sions</hi> Humiliation;) the other two,<note place="margin">Biga in Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah.</note> to the <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> (in <hi>Sions</hi> Exaltation.) The two former ſet forth unto us <hi>Sions</hi> Humiliation; Her being in Captivity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sions</hi> Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation.</note> which enforce Her to pray unto God for her Deliverance.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37758:24"/>The two latter do ſhaddow out her Exaltation;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sions</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation.</note> her being delivered out of captivity: which obligeth her to praiſe God for being delivered. But they do all concenter toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and meet in one, like the myſtical Wheels in <hi>Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> viſion,<note place="margin">Exek. 1.16.</note> at the River <hi>Chebar, Ezek.</hi> 1.16. For there is <hi>Rota in Rota;</hi> A Wheel in a Wheel; and ſo they wheel round, like the Wheel of Fortune: If I may, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, reſemble the Wheel of Divine Providence to that, which they call the Wheel of Fortune.</p>
            <p>But then the queſtion may be moved by ſome, What the Wheel of Fortune is, to which I reſemble the Wheel of Divine Providence.</p>
            <p>For ſatisfaction therefore of thoſe that are ignorant; and better remembrance of thoſe that have forgot it;<note place="margin">Rota For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae.</note> and Wheel of Fortune, as it is called, runs in this manner; Religion, peace; Peace, plenty; Plenty, pride; Pride, war; War, poverty; Poverty, religion; Religion, peace; and ſo it runs round in a circular motion, the one ſtill producing the other. In like manner run the Wheels of my Text.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt God (for Sin, which is the cauſe of all puniſhment; &amp; Captivity,<note place="margin">Rota Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntiae.</note> is the greateſt of puniſhments to a People or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) doth ſuffer his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his People, to go into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</item>
               <item>Secondly, When <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods People, are in captivity, they pray, or ought to pray, unto God for deliverance out of captivity.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, Upon the Prayers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods People, when they are in captivity, the Lord will, and doth turn the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of his People.</item>
               <item>Laſtly, When upon the Prayers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the People of God, God hath been pleaſed at length to turn the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of his People, it is the duty of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all Gods People, by way of thankfulneſs, to rejoyce and be glad in God their Saviour; and (with the bleſſed Virgin) to ſing their <hi>Magnificats</hi> unto him,<note place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.47. for turning their captivity, and giving deliverance to them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The neglect of which duty of thankfulneſs, by way of return, to celebrate Gods power, and to magnifie his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in being joyful and glad, for turning their captivity,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37758:24"/>doth turn into ſin; and ſin doth turn away Gods preſence and favour from his People; and ſo God, by with-drawing his preſence and favour from his people, doth ſuffer them to go into captivity; and when they are in captivity, they pray for deliverance; and upon their prayers God doth turn their captivity; and when they are delivered out of captivity, they ought to rejoyce and be glad for it.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how the Wheels run round, and follow one another. Unthankfulneſs, in not being joyful and glad for deliverance out of captivity, cauſeth God to ſuffer <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his People, to go into captivity; Captivity then begets Prayer; Prayer breeds Deliverance; and Deliverance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth Thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the myſtical Wheels in our Topical Charriot of of the Text; of which there is a <hi>Biga</hi> in the <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> and a <hi>Biga</hi> in the <hi>Hallelujah;</hi> two in the one, and two in the other. The two former are turned from us; but yet not ſo turned away from us, but that, by our unthankfulneſs, in not rejoycing and being glad as we ought, they may turn again to us. The two latter turn to us, and we are to turn to them; and ſo to turn to them, that the other turn not again to us.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Churches <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah:</hi>
               </note>My Province is to ſpeak of the Spokes of the two laſt Wheels in the Churches <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> which are delineated to us in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>When the Lord turneth the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of his People, then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be right glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here our two Wheels do run upon two Tracts, upon two Lines, upon two Terms.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Cum,</hi> When,</item>
               <item>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Tum.</hi> Then.</item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <l>When the Lord turneth the Captivity of his People,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be right glad.</l>
            </q>
            <list>
               <item>In the Former, There is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A <hi>Suppoſition.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In the Later, There is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A <hi>Impoſition.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37758:25"/>
            <p>The one is <hi>Hypothetical,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
               </note> and ſuppoſeth <hi>Beneficium,</hi> a Mercy, or Deliverance on Gods part: That God will turn the Captivity of his People.</p>
            <p>The other is <hi>Categorical,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
               </note> and impoſeth <hi>Officium,</hi> a Duty, or a Service to be performed on his Peoples part: When God hath turned the Captivity of his People.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The Firſt, is <hi>Preſumed.</hi> The One, is <hi>Poſitive.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Second, is <hi>Aſſumed.</hi> The Other, is <hi>Illative.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>Cum</hi> tells us, that Deliverance of Gods people out of Captivity will come.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Tum</hi> tells us, that when Deliverance of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple out of Captivity is come, then their thankfulneſs for ſuch a deliverance muſt come likewiſe: then they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and be glad for it.</p>
            <p>They both run, in the Future Tenſe, according to St. <hi>Hierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> in loc.</note> from the Seventy Interpreters: <hi>Cum converte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> or, <hi>Cum averterit:</hi> When God ſhall have turned, or turned away the Captivity of his people, then they ſhall rejoyce, and be glad. And may they never have their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity turned away from them, who, when their Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is turned away, will not return their thankfulneſs to God, by being joyful, and glad, for its returning!</p>
            <p>But the former is in the Preſent Tenſe (according to the Tranſlation of <hi>Tremellius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tremell.</note> 
               <hi>Reducente Jehovah reducem Populi ſui turmam</hi>) as if God were at the preſent returning their Captivity, which being turned away, Jacob <hi>ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be right glad.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In plain Engliſh, <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall dance a Galliard for joy; and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be glad at the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Applicatio Prophetiae.</note>Now to bring this Prophecy (which was foretold to the Jews, and afterwards, although a long while after, fullfilled for them) from <hi>Palaeſtine</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> and from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>London;</hi> and to apply it to our ſelves here preſent, who have been lately delivered from a more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous than Babylonian Captivity: (for in <hi>Babel,</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> there was only a Confuſion of Tongues and Languages; but here, in Great <hi>Britain,</hi> there was a Confuſion of Hearts
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37758:25"/>and Affections: we did agree in nothing but in diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) Shall nor we, ſince God hath been pleaſed to fullfil this Prophecy for us alſo, and hath turned our Captivity, turn the Tenſe, as God hath turned the Times? Since God hath turned our Condition, and from an Imperative Mood, in which we were commanded, hath brought us to the Optative Mood, which we long deſired; And from <hi>Utinam veniat al quando tempus!</hi> Would to God the time would come! he hath reduced us to the time, we then did wiſh, and do now enjoy, and wiſh that it may long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue; And ſince from a Subjunctive Mood (in which we were brought under, and ſubjected to our Fellow-Subjects, who then did tyrannize and Lord it over us, and in that condition and ſtate we could not be Potentialls, to free us from that miſery and ſlavery we were in) God hath, out of his infinite goodneſs, brought us to an Infinitve Mood of proſperity and happineſs, which (Bleſſed be God) we now are in: though contrary to the nature of the Infinitive Mood, which hath neither Number, nor Perſon, nor Nominative Caſe: We have now both diſtinction of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and difference of Perſons, and can nominate, and lay open our Caſes in the Courts of Juſtice; which then, (although we were not Supines, but Gerunds, both in <hi>Di, Do, Dum;</hi> for ſome were forced to dye; others to give money to ſave themſelves, and all were dumb, and durſt not open their mouths, to ſpeak againſt their proceedings;) we were neceſſitated to bear without any redreſs; Shall not we, I ſay, now, in the Indicative Mood, ſhew our ſelves thankful for ſo great a mercy, which is infinite, and beyond expreſſion? Surely, we are not worthy to have had ſo great a deliverance vouchſafed to us, if, with the turning of our Captivity, with the Times, we do not alſo alter, and turn the Tenſe. And therefore, ſeeing God hath turned that Tenſe, which was in the Future with the Jews, into the Preterperfect Tenſe with us; and that, which he did then but promiſe, for the preſent, to the Jews, he hath now perfectly fullfilled for us, in turning our Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity; which, though he did promiſe to them, he did not a long while after perform for them: Oh let us, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what great things God hath done for us, and recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37758:26"/>with our ſelves, that God (to uſe the Apoſtles phraſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.40.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40.) hath provided better things for us, than he did for the Jews, to whom this promiſe was made. For, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.39. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them died,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.39.</note> not receiving the promiſe; which, Bleſſed be God, we have enjoyed. Upon the meditation of ſo great a mercy, let us take up that ſpeech of <hi>Iphicra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> a valiant Captain of the <hi>Athenians;</hi> which, though it were modeſtly ſpoken by him, yet let us piouſly apply it to our ſelves; and, in a grateful manner, let us confeſs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from how great baſeneſs and miſery, to what great glory and felicity, God hath advanced us; and ſo, in the name of God, the great <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Turner of Captivities, as we are bound in duty, by way of thankfulneſs, for ſuch an extraordinary, and undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved favour, let us, I ſay, turn the Tenſe, as God hath turned the Times, and change the Future into the Preſent Tenſe with him, in being, now for the preſent, and ſtill hereafter, for the future (as <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> are enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Text) joyful, and right glad, for it.</p>
            <p>So that, without further Ambages of Words, or Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutions of Phraſes,<note place="margin">In this <hi>Biga</hi> 2. Topicks.</note> in the <hi>Biga</hi> of the Churches <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah,</hi> there are 2. Spokes only to be ſpoken of, 2. Tropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Topicks to be illuſtrated.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>1. The <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The <hi>Quid factum</hi> What is done.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>2. The <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The <hi>Quid faciendum</hi> What is to be done.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Quid factum.</note>Firſt, I ſhall relate unto you the <hi>Quid factum,</hi> What is done.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Quid facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note>Secondly, I ſhall declare the <hi>Quid faciendum,</hi> What is, or ought to be done.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Former is <hi>Ex parte Dei;</hi> and ſo I ſhall inform you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Dei.</note> what God hath done, on his part, for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Ex. parte Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli.</note>The Latter is <hi>Ex parte Populi;</hi> and ſo I ſhall inforce un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, what Gods People ought, to do, on their part, in requital to him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. What sdone.</note>The Firſt ſheweth, what God hath done for his people:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37758:26"/>He hath turned their Captivity: <hi>Revertente Domino Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitatem Populi ſui:</hi> When the Lord turneth the Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his People.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. What is to be done.</note>The Second ſets forth, what Gods people ought to do for him, in turning their Captivity: They ought to return thanks to God, in being joyful and glad, for turning their Captivity: <hi>Exultabit</hi> Jacob, <hi>laetabitur</hi> Iſrael: Then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be right glad.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sionis <hi>Reductio.</hi>
               </note>In the Former, there is <hi>Sionis Reductio, Sions</hi> Reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or bringing back; <hi>Sions</hi> Reſtauration; or, the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Sions</hi> Captivity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sionis <hi>Exultatio:</hi>
               </note>In the Latter, there is <hi>Sionis Exultatio, Sions</hi> Exultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Acclamation; <hi>Sions</hi> Rejoycing for the returning of her Captivity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt Wheel in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah.</hi>
               </note>I begin with the firſt Tropical Topick, which is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Quid factum; Ex parte Dei:</hi> What God hath done for his part, in the behalf, and for the behoof of his people. <hi>Reduxit Captivitatem plebis ſuae:</hi> He hath turned the Captivity of his people.<note place="margin">Sionis <hi>Reductio:</hi> or, The tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Sions</hi> Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</note> Which is the firſt Wheel in the Churches <hi>Hallelujah;</hi> and is <hi>Sionis Reductio; Sions</hi> Reduction and Reſtauration; or, the turning of <hi>Sions</hi> Captivity.</p>
            <p>In the turning of which Wheel, I ſhall keep my ſelf cloſe to the Records of ſacred Scripture, both for the Confirmation and Illuſtration of it. For, though the teſtimonies of humane Writers might furniſh us with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of evidence, to demonſtrate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I.</hi> Quid factum: Ex parte D.i.</note> and make good the truth of it, in matter of Fact; that God hath turned the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of his people: Yet, becauſe the Writings of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, which were their Enemies, are Eccentrical, and have no relation to the people of God, otherwiſe than as they help to fill and make up their ſtories; I ſhall wave their atteſtation to confirm our declaration, and reſt only in the proof, I meet with, in the Chronicles of holy Writ, which ſet forth both the acts and paſſages of Gods people ſince the Creation, and are, without any other ſupplement, of ſufficient Authority, both to reſtifie the truth of them, and to gain credit and belief to them.</p>
            <p>And here, not to ſpeak of the Antediluvian times, when, in the dayes of <hi>Seth,</hi> God reſtored Religion, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37758:27"/>a long time had been ſuppreſſed by the Enemies of God, the wicked Sons of men,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.26.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.26. Nor yet to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how God did deliver his Church and People by <hi>Noah,</hi> from the hands of thoſe that did uſurp Authority over them; and preſerve it by his obedience, in the Ark, when he deſtroyed all fleſh upon the earth with a Deluge of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.23.<note place="margin">Gen. 7.23.</note> Nor yet to relate, how God, after the Flood, delivered his Church and People from the tyranny of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and his Complices, by the Confuſion of Tongues at <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.9. Nor yet to tell you, how God preſerved and delivered his Church in the time of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Patriarchs, before their going into <hi>Egypt;</hi> of which you may read in the Book of <hi>Geneſis.</hi> I ſhall begin the Province, which I have undertaken, with the Captivity of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and the hard uſage, and ſlavery which they ſuffered in the houſe of bondage,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.2.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2. Under <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and his Task-Maſters, while they were in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and how God turned cheir Captivity, and delivered them out of it.</p>
            <p>And ſo, if you look into the Book of <hi>Exodus,</hi> which hath its name from the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> you ſhall find, that, according to Gods promiſe made to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13. After the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been in affliction four hundred years in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the houſe of ſlavery, the term which God himſelf doth give it, <hi>Domus Servitutis,</hi> the Houſe of Bondage, as you heard before <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.2.</note> It came to paſs, when they never thought of it, nor could believe it, at the end of four hundred and thirty years, even the ſelf ſame day that God had appointed, it came to paſs, that all the Hoſts of the Lord went out from the Land of <hi>Egypt:</hi> as you may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inform your ſelves, both of their departure, and the manner of it,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.41.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.41. And after God had ſo miraculouſly turned their Captivity, by the hands of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> you may read likewiſe, how joyful and glad they were for it. For, as it is there recorded, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> with the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſang a Song of Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto the Lord,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.1.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1. Nor were the Women wanting to celebrate with joy that great Solemnity: For, as <hi>Moſes</hi> doth certifie us, Miriam <hi>the Propheteſs, the Siſter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37758:27"/>of</hi> Aaron, <hi>took a Timbrel in her hand; and all the Women went out after her, with Timbrells, and with Dances, Singing unto the Lord,</hi> Exod. 15.20.21. So that,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.20.21.</note> from their preſident and example, not men only, but women alſo, muſt rejoyce at the deliverance of Gods people out of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity; and muſt celebrate it with ſinging, and dancing, and all ſigns of joy.</p>
            <p>And that the remembrance of ſo great a benefit of their deliverance might not ſlip out of their memories, but be continued to all Poſterity, God enjoyns the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at the ſame time, to celebrate the Paſſover,<note place="margin">Exod. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.6. (Which was a ſign, not only of the deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells paſſing over the Houſes of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he ſlew all the firſt born of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 12.27.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.27. But alſo of their paſſing over the Red Sea, out of the Land of <hi>Egypt.</hi>) And at that Paſſover, God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to teach their Children the meaning of it;<note place="margin">Exod. 14.22.</note> that they alſo might tell their Children, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Children; and ſo the Generations yet unborn,<note place="margin">Exod. 13.8.</note> by this means, might both know what the Lord had done for them, in turning their Captivity; and alſo be joyful and glad in praiſing the Lord for ſuch their deliverance,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5.6. Yea, that they might not forget his turning of their Captivity out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but that it might take a deeper impreſſion in them;<note place="margin">Joſ. 4.21.22.</note> God himſelf again becomes their Monitour; and, at the giving or the Law, contained in the Decalogue, upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> in the Preface to it, he uſeth this, as the ſole Argument to preſs them to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,<note place="margin">Evod. 20.2.</note> in obſerving of it, becauſe he was the Lord their God, and he had choſen them to be his People,<note place="margin">Deut. 5.6.</note> whom he had brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and from the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.2.</p>
            <p>I will not ſtand to tell you, how God delivered them from the hands of their Enemies, that would have Captiv'd them in their paſſage through the Wilderneſs, under the Conduct of <hi>Moſes</hi> their Prince, and <hi>Joſhuah</hi> their Captain General;<note place="margin">Joſ. 14.1.</note> and how God brought them into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which he had promiſed to their fore-Fathers, and which was divided unto them by <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> according to their ſeveral inheritances. The other Books of <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37758:28"/>his Pentateuch, and the Hiſtory of <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> after <hi>Moſes</hi> his death, will ſufficiently acquaint you, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 14.1.</p>
            <p>But in the Calender of the Judges, you ſhall find it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred and inrolled, how many times God did ſuffer them, by reaſon of their ſins, to go into Captivity; and how often he ſold them into the hands of their Enemies,<note place="margin">Judg. 2.14.</note> to be Lords over them; and yet again, upon their prayers and cries unto God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.12.</note> when they were oppreſſed, and in Captivity, you may read likewiſe, how God turned again their Captivity, and freed them from the hands of their Enemies. For which ſeveral deliverances, if they did not expreſs their thankfulneſs, by being joyful and glad (as <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> are here enjoyned in my Text) they were moſt unworthy of ſo great mercies, becauſe they had great cauſe to rejoyce and be glad for them.</p>
            <p>Thus you may read in thoſe ſacred Archiues, how God turned their Captivity from <hi>Chuſhan-Riſhathaim,</hi> King of <hi>Aram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 3.8.</note> or <hi>Syria,</hi> by the hand of <hi>Othniel, Jud.</hi> 3.8. How he turned their Captivity from <hi>Eglon,</hi> King of <hi>Moab,</hi> by the hand of <hi>Ehud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Jud.</hi> 3.14. How he turned their Captivity from the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> with an Oxe-Goad, by <hi>Shamgar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 7.31.</note> 
               <hi>Jud.</hi> 3.31. Thus you may read, how he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Captivity, when he had ſold them into the hand of <hi>Jabin,</hi> King of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and delivered them from <hi>Siſera</hi> his chief Captain, which dwelt in <hi>Haroſheth</hi> of the Gentiles, by the hand of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>Jud.</hi> 4.23. How he turned their Captivity from the <hi>Midianites</hi> (into whoſe hands he had ſold them 7. years, becauſe they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord) by the hand of <hi>Gedeon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 7.25.</note> who was called <hi>Jerubbaal, Jud.</hi> 7.25, How he turned their Captivity from the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> by the hand of <hi>Jephtah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 11.32.</note> 
               <hi>Jud.</hi> 11.32. And, to be brief, thus you may read, how God delivered them from the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines,</hi> and turned their Captivity from them,<note place="margin">Judg. 14.14. &amp; 15.15. &amp; 16.3.</note> firſt by <hi>Sampſon, Jud.</hi> 14.14.15.15.16.3. And afterwards by <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.10. For which ſeveral deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of Captivity and Slavery, which they ſuſtained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Enemies hands,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.10.</note> there is no queſtion, but they did all rejoyce, and were exceedingly glad; becauſe, when they were oppreſſed, and vexed by their Enemies,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37758:28"/>they cried exceedingly to be delivered: although we find none of their Hymns of rejoycing, and Pſalms of joy, to be regiſtred in thoſe holy Records; excepting that Song of Thankfulneſs of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 5.1.</note> which they did exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantly ſing, after their renowned Victory over <hi>Siſera;</hi> as you may read, <hi>Jud.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p>Nor will I inſiſt to relate unto you, how God delivered the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the hands of their enemies in the time of the Kings: you may ſpare me that trouble, if you pleaſe, at your leiſure, to revolve and peruſe thoſe holy Chronicles, which are there ſet down concerning the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that ſignal and famous Deliverance from the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Babylon,</hi> after threeſcore and ten years, which they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by reaſon of their ſins; and from which they were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly delivered by Gods mercy, challengeth a more than ordinary attention and obſervation.</p>
            <p>Which captivity of theirs, as it was fore-told by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 25.9.10, 11.</note> and other of the Lords Servants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; ſo was their return fore-prophecied likewiſe;<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 5.26.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they would not believe or give credit to either. Yet had they not been ſo ſtupid in judgement,<note place="margin">2 Kings 20.17.18. &amp; 23.27. &amp; 24.1.2.</note> and excoecated and blinded in their underſtanding; having eys to ſee,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.6.</note> but (as the Prophet ſpeaks of them) would not ſee; and ears to hear, but would not hear; and hearts to underſtand, but would not underſtand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9.10. They might as well have believed their return from captivity,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.9.10.</note> as being under the yoak in <hi>Babylon,</hi> they were ſenſible of it; both being alike fore-told by the Prophets.</p>
            <p>However, that the Word of the Lord, ſpoken by the mouth of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet, might be accompliſhed,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.22.</note> the Lord ſtirred up the ſpirit of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezra 1.1. &amp; 4.4.5: &amp; 5.3.</note> to make a Proclamation throughout all his Kingdom; and cauſed it to be put in writing for their return out of <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> which accordingly came to paſs, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the oppoſition of their enemies: For as you may read in the Books of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> they came again to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> every one to his own City, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.4. &amp; 5.3.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to tell you how joyful theſe people
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37758:29"/>were, when God had turned their captivity from them. If, you pleaſe to turn to that Pſalm, which, from their return is intituled <hi>In Convertendo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.1.2.</note> you may ſufficiently ſatisfie your ſelves in it: for the Kingly Prophet begins that Pſalm with <hi>In Convertendo Dominus Captivitatem</hi> Sion; <hi>When the Lord turned the captivity of</hi> Sion, <hi>we were like unto them that dream: Then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with joy, Pſal.</hi> 126.1.2. That is, they were like men in a dream, that felt ineffable joy, and incredible comfort; and yet they doubted whether it were true or but a dream:<note place="margin">Acts 12.4.5, 6.</note> Even as we read of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Acts of the Apoſtles, when he was impriſoned by <hi>Herod,</hi> and deſtined to be brought forth to the people, and to be put to death: upon the prayers of the Church interceding with God for him, the Angel of the Lord came into the Priſon to him, whiles he was faſt aſleep, and dream'd not of it: and ſmite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him on the ſide, he raiſed him up, cauſing his Chains to fall from his hands; and being awaked the Angel bid him ariſe, and to gird himſelf, and to bind on his Sandales, and to caſt his Garment about him, and to follow him. Now when <hi>Peter</hi> had thus done, and followed the Angel out of Priſon, and was come abroad, the Text faith, that he wiſt not that it was true which was done by the Angel that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him,<note place="margin">Acts 12.7.8, 9.</note> but thought he had ſeen a Viſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.7.8.9. In like manner was it with the Jews, that were captived in <hi>Babylon:</hi> after their captivity was turned, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they felt ſuch joy and rejoycing; ſuch gladneſs and comfort, as was as much incredible as inutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>But leaving the captivity of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the People of God, in former times, and in forraign parts, with the returning of it, let us return to our ſelves, and take notice of the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and ſlavery, which God of his unſpeakable mercy, of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter days, hath freed us from, and turned away from us, here at home, in our own Country. And here, not to tarry, or make a Manſion on; but only to touch, and make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, thoſe two remarkable and famous deliverances from captivity, both Corporal and Spiritual, which God was pleaſed, of his meer grace and goodneſs, to vouchſafe to us his People of <hi>England.</hi> How can we forget thoſe two me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37758:29"/>years, of One thouſand, five hundred,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1588.</note> eighty and eight; and, of One thouſand, ſix hundred, and five: the one in the laſt Century, the other in this Century?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1605.</note> In the former of which, God did mightily deliver us his People, from an open Invaſion by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> from abroad; and in the latter, did moſt miraculouſly free us from a ſecret undermining at home: Both plotted by <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and acted by <hi>Papiſts.</hi> The one by Strand, the other by Land: The one by Strangers and Foraigners at Sea; the other by home-born Subjects aſhoar; The one upon our Coaſts; the other near, and under our Courts: The one by Shipping, with Swords, Powder, Match, and Bullets; the other in a Vault or Cellar, with Croues of Iron, Barrels of Powder, and Matchleſs Billets: Both which egregious, and famous deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, from the enemies of our Engliſh <hi>Sion,</hi> are not to be buried in oblivion, (as they have been too much forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſome that would have ſeemed to be the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion amongſt us) but ought to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by all true Engliſhmen; and to be perpetuated by them, with red letters in Fames Calendar, to all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe theſe two great deliverances are paſt the memory of moſt men now living; and moſt of us here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent know nothing of them, ſave only by reading, tradition, and common hear-ſay, I ſhall paſs them over with the bare remembrance and naming of them. And ſo, leaving them to be ſolemnized in their proper times, I ſhall addreſs my ſelf to ſpeak of that lateſt deliverance out of captivity and thraldom, which, not above two years ſince, God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to vouchſafe unto us, and is ſtill freſh in every mans, and almoſt in every childs memory, and is moſt proper to be treated of at this time.</p>
            <p>Know then, that we may come to be more ſenſible of it, when, by reaſon of our ſins, and high ingratitude towards God for our long continued peace and proſperity, above all the Nations and Kingdoms round about us, God had moſt juſtly ſuffered us to be infeſted with inteſtine Arms, and a civil War, (which of all others is moſt dangerous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious) our fellow-Subjects riſing up in rebellion againſt their Prince; and had permitted thoſe Rebels to be ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37758:30"/>in Arms againſt their Liege Lord and Soveraign, His late Majeſty, of ever bleſſed memory; by reaſon whereof, we came to loſe, not only our Religion, Laws, Liberties, and Proprieties, (the only things which the Rebels preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they took up Arms to defend and preſerve from viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) but alſo our moſt gracious King, <hi>King Charles the firſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (<hi>Infandum &amp; immane nefas!</hi> A crime not to be ſpoken, or thought of, without horrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement!) whoſe Honour and Perſon they had taken ſo many Oaths of Allegiance, Proteſtations, Covenants and Vows, and theſe in a Sacramental manner, to defend and maintain, ſave and keep ſecure from all violence; all which notwithſtanding they did, (under a colour of juſtice, to juſtifie their proceedings, which were no ways juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, bvt unparalleld by all former preſidents ſince the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) moſt inhumanely, unchriſtianly, and butcherly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him, becauſe he would not, in the leaſt, give way to violate, either our Religion, Laws, Liberties, and Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but did moſt Chriſtianly, Manly, and Kingly maintain them, even with the loſs of his life; dying both the Churches and Kingdoms Martyr, that they ſhould not be revelled and raviſhed by them. And, when God had as juſtly ſuffered us to be made Vaſſals and Slaves to our fellow-Subjects, (a juſt reward for our diſobedience, formality, and neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, in that we would not ſubmit to, ſtand by, and adhere, as we ought, to our natural and lawful Prince) and had let us continue for many years in that Slavery, a ſlavery worſe than that of Gods people, either in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon:</hi> (for they were in bondage under Strangers and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners abroad, which was ſomewhat more tolerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it could not be any ways remedied; but our ſlavery was under our own Brethren, Kindred, and Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at home; under ſuch fellows, ſome of them, as were not our Fellows, but formerly our Servants; and which ſervile condition, had it not been for our puſillanimity, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, and falſe-heartedneſs, might have been prevented by us, and not incumbent on us.) At length the ſame good God, who is righteous in all his ways, and holy in all his works,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.17.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the only Averruncator, and and turner away of all evil from his people, out of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37758:30"/>mercy, which endureth for ever, and never faileth them that put their truſt in it, was pleaſed to take notice of the ſighs, and hear the groans, and hearken to the prayers of his unworthy people, and did unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly turn this captivity away from us.</p>
            <p>It would not be a Parergon, or a relation from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if I ſhould recount unto you, how his SaCRed Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, now ſurviving, (and long may he live for the glory of God, and the honour of theſe Nations, to be a comfort to his Friends, and a terrour to his Enemies!) to recover his own Rights, and to reſtore his peoples Liberties, had, both by Himſelf and his Miniſters, mediated with his Allies and Friends, uſing all means poſſible and imaginable abroad; As alſo, that his Loyal Subjects had left nothing unattemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but did <hi>omnem movere lapidem,</hi> (to make uſe of the Latine Proverb) uſe the utmoſt of their endeavours, which the Wit, or Art of man could ſuggeſt, and their induſtry put in practice, for to redeem and recover themſelves, and their relations out of that unparalleld ſlavery they were in at home. And yet, notwithſtanding his Majeſties negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons abroad, and his Subjects aſſiduous machinations at home, either through perfidious treachery, or too credulous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency, all their projects, deſigns, and plots, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Plin. Nat. Hiſt. <hi>10.58.</hi>
               </note> which the natural Philoſophers and Hiſtorians ſpeak of, thoſe addle eggs which bring forth nothing but wind, came to be fruſtate and of no effect.</p>
            <p>Nor may we wonder at Gods moſt wiſe, though ſecret diſpenſation of affairs in this kind: for he doth ſuffer his people (as we may obſerve in the holy Scripture) to be in affliction, and in captivity, and to continue in them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their prayers and endeavours to get out of them: to make them, by humility and meekneſs; by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and long-ſuffering; by faith and invocation, meet, and fitted to entertain, with more thankfulneſs and joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the mercy of their deliverance, when he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move their affliction, and turn their captivity. And though the time of captivity may ſeem long to us, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the irkſomneſs and tediouſneſs of it;<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.4.</note> yet in Gods account it is not ſo: for a thouſand years, as the Pſalmiſt and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> have it, are but as a day in reſpect of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37758:31"/>him,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.4. And as our ways are not as his ways, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.29. ſo neither are our times, as his times. Though we be ready,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.29.</note> as we think, to come out of thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſlavery, ſo ſoon as we are come into it; yet we are not ready in Gods account,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and therefore we muſt rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon again. Gods time is not yet come, in which he hath determined to bring us out of ſlavety, and to turn our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, when we think it high time to be delivered and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricated out of it: and therefore God having ſuffered us, through our own fault, to come into captivity &amp; ſlavery, did let us remain ſo long time in it, that ſo our reſtauration and return out of it, might be more acceptable to us, &amp; we more fit to embrace it with thankfulneſs, when he ſhould turn it.</p>
            <p>And give me leave to tell you likewiſe, that when we were in that deplorable condition, in that remedileſs eſtate, in the loweſt of our fortunes; when we were utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſpiſed, as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, and exceedingly filled with contempt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 123.3.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.3. When our ſouls were filled with the ſcornful reproof of thoſe that were grown wealthy; and with the deſpitefulneſs of them that were ſo proud,<note place="margin">V. 4.</note> 
               <hi>V.</hi> 4. When our Bodies were captiv'd and under Hatches, (a puniſhment never excogitated by the worſt of Tyrants, nor practiſed in the fierceſt of Perſecutions) and they did ſuffer men to ride over our heads,<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.11.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal,</hi> 66.11. When we were <hi>vincti,</hi> Priſoners indeed; but yet not <hi>vincti spei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 9.12.</note> (as the Prophets expreſſion is,) Priſoners of hope, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.12. for we were without all hope, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of freeing our ſelves out of that Labyrinth of miſery; when thoſe Matchiviallians, or matchleſs Villains of the times, in their modern policy, like <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, had ſaid, <hi>Go to, let us build a City and Tower of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that may reach to Heaven, and get us a name ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.4. when they were in the height of their tyrannie, and we in the depth of our ſlavery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then did the Proverb, not more old than true, (according to St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ſentence) verify it ſelf to our misbelieving ſouls:<note place="margin">Aug. de. Temp. Ser. <hi>89.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ubi deſinit humanuns, ibi incipit Divinum auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Where mans means of help do fail;</l>
               <l>There Gods means do moſt avail.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37758:31"/>
            <p>For now God Almighty, (who, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſtiles him, is <hi>Adjutor in opportunitatibus, &amp; in tribulatione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal</hi> 9.9. A defence for the oppreſſed, even a refuge in due time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) making our great extremity, his gracious opportunity, did take the King, his Vicegerents, and the Churches, his Spouſes cauſe into his own hands, which he had ſeen to be ſo ill managed by others; and ſeeing the enemies of both to be implacable, by reaſon of their many proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes; inſomuch that ſome of them had ſaid, (if Fame hath not given a miſ-report) concerning the one, they would never be reconciled to that curſed Family, (<hi>Vox faucibus haeret,</hi> The words ſtick in my throat at the pronunciation of them!) And of the other, they would not leave a Prieſt to piſs againſt the Wall, (ſo great friends were they, as they pretended, to Religion) but they would Pave the High-ways, from <hi>York</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> with the Churches ſtones; At length, when thoſe enemies of <hi>Sion,</hi> and of <hi>David,</hi> thought all was Cock-ſure, (as we uſe to ſay) and that they had ſettled themſelves ſo faſt, as they could never be removed; then did God come down, (to ſpeak in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe) to ſee the <hi>Babel</hi> of their Government; and ſeeing they could not be ſtopped by men, from doing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they imagined to do, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.6. God himſelf,<note place="margin">Gen. 11.6.</note> to abate their pride, and aſſwage their malice, did over-turn the Model, and overthrow the Fabrick of their intended <hi>Babel.</hi> And, as at the confuſion of <hi>Babel,</hi> God, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Church and People under tyranny, did divide <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> and his Complices, and ſcatter them over the face of the earth, by the confuſion of their tongues and languages; So here likewiſe, God, to redeem us his people, out of the ſlavery and captivity we were in, did divide the hearts and affections of our <hi>Nimrods,</hi> and their Complices, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting their conſultations, and confounding their devices. For when every ones ambition did ſpurre him on to be the chiefeſt, and to get the rains of Government into his own hands, and to pull down that plat-form of Government which they had begun to build; then did God deſtroy the Counſels of thoſe <hi>Achitophels,</hi> which were accounted as Oracles in thoſe days,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16 23.</note> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. and cauſed ſome of them, though not to hang themſelves, as <hi>Achitophel</hi> did,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37758:32"/>2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23. yet to be hang'd by others;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.23.</note> and ſcattered the others over the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>Now this God did bring to paſs, by means unthought of by us, and by ſuch means as we did never dream of. And whiles our captivity was thus in turning, we were like the Jews, in the return of their captivity: For as they could do nothing of themſelves, but were helpleſs; no more could we,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.22.</note> but were altogether hopeleſs; no more ſtirred up the heart of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> (which was the Procatarctical cauſe of their returning) to make a Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation throughout his Kingdom, for the Jews to return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own Country, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.22. So did God (the ſame yeſterday,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> to day, and the ſame for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.) ſtirre up the ſpirit of our <hi>Cyrus,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to ſend a Declaration of his good will and affection to all his people; with a promiſe of an Act of Indemnity and Oblivion, to all that would accept of it, if he ſhould return with honour and ſecurity into his Kingdoms. And ſo by this means, God, the great <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, moving the hearts of the people to accept of what the King had propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, (an expedient which we did never dream would take effect;) and the effect enſuing, which we did never dream would come to paſs; yea, and do ſtill dream that it ſhould ſo come to paſs; (for here we cannot but confeſs with the Jews in their return out of captivity; and make uſe of the Prophets expreſſion, concerning their return out of capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,<note place="margin">Pſal. 126.3.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we were like to men in a dream, in the manner, and mannaging of the great revolution and change of the times) the All-wiſe, and All-wonder-working God, who is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the only turner of captivities, and redeemet of Captives, did over-turn the devices of our enemies, who kept us Captives; and by captivating them, did turn away our captivity from us.</p>
            <p>It is ſtoried by <hi>Livie,</hi> that great Hiſtorian among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that when the <hi>Romans</hi> might have given a Law to the <hi>Graecians</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Livie</hi> in Dec.</note> in the ſolemn time of their <hi>Iſthmian</hi> Games, which were celebrated in <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> every five years, their General, unexpectedly by an Herauld, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed freedom to all the Cities of <hi>Greece:</hi> Which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37758:32"/>at firſt did ſo amaze the <hi>Graecians,</hi> that they did not believe it to be true. But when it was proclaimed the ſecond time, the <hi>Graecians</hi> gave ſuch a ſhout, that the very Birds flying in the Ait were aſtoniſhed therewith, and fell dead to the ground.</p>
            <p>To apply this ſtory to our preſent purpoſe: I cannot, ſay, I was in <hi>London</hi> when his Majeſty ſent (and bleſſed be God for moving his Majeſty ſo to ſend) his gracious Letters from <hi>Breda,</hi> bearing date the 14 th. of <hi>April, Anno Domini</hi> 1660. to the Houſes of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons then aſſembled in Parliament; with his Letters and Declarations to the then Lord General, and Officers of the Army; as alſo his Letters and Declaration to the Lord Mayor, the Aldermen, and Common Council of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive City of <hi>London</hi> (for ſo his Majeſty was graciouſly pleaſed to grace the City with that Title, which then it did not deſerve, in that his gracious Letter ſo directed to them:) But being in <hi>Italy,</hi> at my return from <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> I heard how joyfully thoſe gracious Letters and Declarations were generally received, though by ſome they would not be believed. But on the 8 th. of <hi>May,</hi> that happy day, when the King was proclaimed by Heralds throughout the City, ſuch joy and rejoycing, ſuch feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking of Healths, ſuch Bonfires and fireworks, ſuch Muſick and ringing of Bells, ſuch ſhouting and ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch ovation and triumphant acclamations were made throughout the City then, and the Country afterward, that not only the Birds in the Air might be aſtoniſhed, but the Devils in Hell might be amazed to ſee, contrary to their expectation, ſuch a ſudden change, and ſo ſtrange an alteration. And indeed, a ſtrange change it was; and we cannot but cry out with St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſost.</note> by way of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>! <hi>Verè ſtupendae vices!</hi> A very ſtupendous change it was, and to be much admired, and wondred at! Yea, ſo ſtrange a change it was, that they who were the chief Inſtruments, and Actors of it, were the chiefeſt wonderers at it; and were, as it were, in a dream, that it ſhould be ſo contrived, carried on, and ſo happily effected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abdolominus,</hi> as <hi>Q. Curtius</hi> relates,<note place="margin">Q. Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> being conſtituted King
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37758:33"/>of <hi>Sidonia,</hi> by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, when he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent for from manuring and tilling the Earth, to poſſeſs his Kingdom; and to manage a Scepter inſtead of a Spade; it was ſo ſtrange, and beyond his thoughts, that he would not believe it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> in Annot,</note> And <hi>Iſaacus Angelus,</hi> (if the ſtory be true of him) when he was upon the ſudden advanced to the Empire, though he was Inaugurated into the Throne, and ſetled in the Chair of State, he could not believe that he was Emperour. Whence it is obſerved by wiſe men, that it is ever a ſign of a ſtrange event, when men at the ſight of ought, though they be awake, yet they think they are in a dream. And truly this was our caſe; in this condition were we at the return of our Captivity. For, if we might credit, either Perſons or Letters which came from <hi>London,</hi> (give me leave to ſpeak, as being in <hi>Italy</hi>) which both did write and ſpeak of the wonderful change and turn of our Captivity, whiles it was in the returning; we cannot but ſay again, as we have already, with the Jews in their <hi>Convertendo,</hi> or Pſalm of Return, <hi>Facti ſumus ficut ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niantes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.1.</note> we were like to men in a dream. It was their own expreſſion; we could not believe it; we could not give credit to it; we could not think it would e're come to paſs, although we daily ſaw the wayes to it, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it; it was a happineſs ſo much unlooked, unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and unhoped for, in thoſe unhappy dayes, and times of diſtraction.</p>
            <p>I will not here, <hi>Infandum renovare dolorem</hi> (to make uſe of that Pathetical phraſe, of him in the Poet, which a <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Schollar ſometimes uſurped,<note place="margin">Virg. Aeneid.</note> in another caſe, to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when ſhe asked him, how often he had been whipped: <hi>Infandum Regina jubes renovare dolorem</hi>) renew your grief, or repeat your ſorrows, in this time of joy, by recording, and mentioning, what hardſhip and ſlavery, what ſervitude and vaſſalage, by oppreſſion, taxes, and all kind of ſervile offices (worſe than which the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> impoſed on the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> when they made them Tributaries;<note place="margin">Jol. 9.23.</note> of which you may read, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 9.23.) we ſuffered, and tamely underwent, like ſo many <hi>Iſſachars,</hi> (of whom <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.14.15,</note> in his Prophetical Bleſſing, did give this Character: Iſſachar <hi>is a strong Aſſe, couching down
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37758:33"/>between two burthens: And he ſaw that reſt was good, and the Land that it was pleaſant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>and he bowed his ſhoulders to bear, and became a Servant unto tribute;</hi> as you may ſee it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.14.15. I will no further apply that Prophecy to our ſelves, than to ſay, that we ſaw reſt was good, and our Land was pleaſant; and therefore we bowed our ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to bear, and became Servants to tribute) not only under the height of tyranny, in the time of <hi>Oliver,</hi> the Projectour, rather than Protectour; but alſo, under the laſh of the Stinking <hi>Ramp</hi> (which (Bleſſed be God) is ſince roaſted, if not ſome part of it burned) whiles we were in that our Captivity: Although I cannot but tell you withal, what ſometimes <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſaid to his Companions, and fellow-Sufferers, — <hi>Et haec olim meminiſſe juva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> It will be a kind of joy hereafter, to think of our former ſorrows; and we ſhall take a kind of pleaſure, when we ſhall look back into former times, and compare them with the preſent, to remember, and recount to our Poſterity, what hardſhip and ſufferings we have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, in an honeſt, and a juſt cauſe; that ſo, if occaſion ſhould ſerve, they may not with <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſtart aſide like a deceitful bow; but be encouraged to the like vertuous actions.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall endeavour to make you ſenſible, and let you underſtand, how undiſcernably and inſenſibly, how ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wonderfully, <hi>Ad miraculum uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> even to a miracle, God hath turned that our Captivity. For here I muſt have recourſe again to the Prophets expreſſion, which he there ſets down, by way of thankfulneſs, in the Old Teſtament. <hi>A Domino factum eſt iſtud: &amp; fit mirabile in oculis noſtris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.23.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23. And which the Evangeliſt doth take up with a grateful recordation in the new. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Mat. 21.42.</note> 
               <hi>This was the Lords doing, and it is wonderful in our eyes,</hi> Mat. 21.42. Wonderful it was indeed, as I ſaid before; no man but ſtood in a maze at the ſight of it. Even as St. <hi>John</hi> the Divine, when, being carried away in the Spirit into the Wilderneſs, he ſaw the Woman drunken with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus: when he ſaw her (the Text faith) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37758:34"/>he wondred with great admiration,<note place="margin">Revel. 17.6.</note> 
               <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.6. So here, after the Enemies of Gods truth had been drunk with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus, who died witneſſes to the truth of Chriſt, and of Loyalty to their King, the Vice-gerent of Chriſt; when God turned ſo unexpectedly, and ſo ſuddainly, the ſlavery and captivity we were in, every one wondred with great admiration; every one ſtood in amazement at the ſight of it; every one was ſtupefied, and aſtoniſhed, and beſides his ſenſes at the apprehenſion of it; as if he knew not well, whether he ſaw it awaking, or dreamed of it ſleeping, it was ſo ſtrange. And therefore, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſometimes ſaid in another caſe, to the Jews, when he came to <hi>Nazareth: Hodie impleta eſt haec Scriptura in oculis veſtris;</hi> This day is this Scripture fullfilled in your eyes,<note place="margin">Luk. 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.21. So, I cannot but make uſe of the ſame expreſſion, and ſay unto you: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, This day, if ever, this Scripture of Gods turning the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of his People, here fore-prophecied in my Text, is fullfilled both in your eyes and ears.</p>
            <p>Now, as the Jews, after their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> did celebrate the memorial of it with ſeveral Songs, and Pſalms of Degrees, which from thence are entituled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Cantica graduum,</hi> Songs of Degrees, being fifteen in number that are ſo ſtiled, as you may ſee in the Book of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> from the 120 th. to the 135 th. So the return of our Captivity, being no leſs miraculous, than that of theirs, I ſhould commemorate the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of it, by obſerving the ſeveral ſteps and degrees of our, return (by which, as by ſo many ſteps of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we did aſcend from the <hi>Nadar</hi> and Depth of our ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and miſery, to the <hi>Zenith</hi> of our preſent liberty and proſperity) and ſo, by way of thankfulneſs, affix and annex a Song of rejoycing to every Degree.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the time, like a Step-mother to my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath prevented me ſo, that I cannot ſhew you for the preſent, thoſe ſeveral ſteps (which are ſeven in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as I have obſerved them) by which, as by ſo many Degrees, we did return out of our Captivity; Nor yet make that Muſick which I did deſire, in ſetting thoſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37758:34"/>Hymns of rejoycing, and Paeans of joy, by way of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, to every Degree; I ſhall, inſtead of thoſe <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah's,</hi> which I had conceived for every Degree, make uſe of that Anthem, or Natalitial Ode, which was ſet in the higheſt Key, and was ſung in the Superlative Degree, by the Quire of Heavenly Angells, at the Birth of Chriſt; who is <hi>Chriſtus Dominus,</hi> Chriſt the Lord. And this you ſhall find to be ſet and ſung,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gloria Deo in Excelſis:</hi> Or, <hi>Gloria in Altiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis Deo; &amp; in Terra pax; in homines benevolentia:</hi> Glory be to God on high; Or, in the higheſt; and in Earth peace; good will towards men.</p>
            <p>And ſo, in imitation of that Angelical Quire, on the 29 th. day of <hi>May</hi> (Anniverſarily, it being King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> who is <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> the Lords Chriſt, his birth-day: Said I his birth-day? I might have added, his riſing day too; for it was both: Not only the day of his Nativity; but alſo the day of his Reſurrection: It was his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his ſecond birth-day; the day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, was both born into the world, and reborn, or reſtored to his Kingdoms: The day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he roſe from the Clouds of Infamy, to the Sunſhine of Glory; the day wherein he returned from the Pavilions of exilement, to the Palaces of his inthronement) I ſay, on the 29 th. day of <hi>May,</hi> may we ever (ſaid I may? I ſhould have ſaid we muſt, and ſo I ſay, in the revolution of each year, we muſt ever, as the year comes about, ſing on that happy day, every Engliſh Subject muſt, and I cannot believe, but every true-hearted Engliſh Subject will,) with the multitude of the Heavenly Hoſt, ſing that Genethliacal Anthem, which the Angells did begin in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: <hi>Gloria in Altiſſimis Deo:</hi> Glory be to God in the higheſt Heavens; and on Earth peace; good will towards men. A Song, which I may not improperly call (and I hope without offence to the King of Kings) <hi>Ode Carolina,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> his Carole; or a Carole to be ſung on King <hi>Charles</hi> his birth-day; the day of his double Nativity, both to the World, and to his Throne: By which we ought to give glory to God on high; who then, on that day, did ſend our King from Heaven; and with him, that day, did
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37758:35"/>ſend Peace upon Earth; when we were in Hoſtility and War one with another, by reaſon of his abſence from us; and good will towards men; to Engliſh men eſpecially, in bringing home our King from foreign parts, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with us; and making a good underſtanding between King and People, who ſo long time had been miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and ſo unhappily, by that means, ſo long kept aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and by both, turning our Captivity from us.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt we only, in imitation of the multitude of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells in Heaven, ſing, as an <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> that Natalitial Anthem, which, at the Nativity of Chriſt, when he was born, they did ſing for joy in the fields; but we muſt alſo, in imitation of the multitudes of men upon Earth; ſing the <hi>Hoſannah,</hi> which, at Chriſt his riding in triumph into <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> before his death, they did exultantly ſing within the City. For,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.</note> as the Evangeliſts unanimouſly conſent in the relation of that Hiſtory,<note place="margin">Mark. 11.</note> ſix dayes before the Paſſover,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.</note> when Chriſt was come near to <hi>Bethphage</hi> and <hi>Bethany,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12.</note> by the Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> the Diſciples ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, according to his order, brought him a Colt, and ſpreading their garments, ſet him upon it; and having ſtrewed their garments, and branches of Palm-Trees in the way; the multitudes that went before him, and the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes that followed after him, cried, ſaying, <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> to the Son of <hi>David,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Bleſſed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hoſannah</hi> in the higheſt.</p>
            <p>In like manner, all of us, that profeſs to be Chriſts Diſciples, and Chriſtians, as we do; and all that profeſs to be King <hi>Charles</hi> his Subjects, as all Engliſh men are; upon every 29 th. day of <hi>May,</hi> anniverſarily, we ought to ſing our <hi>Hoſannah</hi> likewiſe. For, on that day, that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py day, as I ſaid before (a day, <hi>è meliore notâ,</hi> (to make uſe of the Poets phraſe) <hi>&amp; niveo ſignanda lapillo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat.</note> Of more than ordinary account; a chief day, to be noted with a white ſtone, and a golden letter, and to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as a high Feſtival,) King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second (<hi>Nulli pietate ſecundus,</hi> that hath not his ſecond for piety and goodneſs) riding in triumph to his Palace at <hi>White-Hall,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37758:35"/>(which before had been <hi>Black-well-Hall,</hi>) through the Streets of <hi>London,</hi> (then his <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or Viſion of Peace, after his return from <hi>Mars</hi> his Camp, the <hi>Acel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama,</hi> or bloody field of War,) accompanied with his Nobility and Gentry in the habit of Souldiers; (what ſaid I, in the habit of Souldiers? ſaid I not amiſs? ſpake I not improperly? No, for it is not unknown, though there was <hi>Species Praeliantium,</hi> yet there were <hi>Voces Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantium;</hi> though they had the habit of Souldiers, yet they had the voices of Singers; and) the multitudes that went before, and the multitudes that followed after him, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaying, <hi>Hoſannah</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, the happy Son of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of moſt happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory: <hi>Bleſſed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna</hi> in Altiſſimis: Hoſannah <hi>in the higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, as you have ſeen, I have turned over the firſt Topical Wheel, in the <hi>Biga</hi> of the Churches <hi>Hallelujah;</hi> which is <hi>Sionis Reductio,</hi> the Reduction, or Returning of <hi>Sions</hi> Captivity: wherein I have ſhewed you the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Quid factum, Ex parte Dei;</hi> What God hath done on his part, for, and in the behalf of his People:<note place="margin">The Second Wheel in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Captivitatem Populi ſui;</hi> He hath turned the Captivity of his People.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now; according to method, proceed to moue the Second Wheel in the <hi>Biga</hi> of the Churches <hi>Hallelujah;</hi> which is <hi>Sionis Exultatio, Sions</hi> Rejoycing,<note place="margin">Sionis <hi>Exultatio.</hi> or, <hi>Sions</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing for her Return.</note> for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of her Captivity; or, for her Return out of Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: which is the next thing to be conſidered, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Quid faciendum, Ex parte Populi;</hi> What Gods People ought to do on their part, and return to God, by way of thankfulneſs, for returning their Captivity: which is expreſſed in the laſt words of my Text: <hi>Exultabit</hi> Jacob,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Quid facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum; Ex parte Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli.</note> 
               <hi>Laetabitur</hi> Iſrael: Then ſhall <hi>Jacob</hi> rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be right glad.</p>
            <p>In which Topical Wheel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if time would permit me to turn it round, there are two Spokes to be ſpoken of likew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Duty enjoyned.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Perſons to perform it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37758:36"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">1. The Duty.</note>Firſt, We ſhould conſider the duty enjoyned; and that is twofold:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Exultation:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Laetation.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
Both which are ſet forth in the two Verbs.
<list>
                     <item>1. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Shall <hi>Rejoyce.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Shall be <hi>Glad.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, We ſhould deſcribe the perſons that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to perform this duty; and they are implyed in the two names,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">2. The Perſons.</note> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.<hi>Jacob.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Then ſhall</hi> Jacob <hi>rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be right glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a duplicity in both, though there ought to be ſimplicity in both.</p>
            <p>The duty is twofold; and the perſons have two names: Sincerity is required in the duty enjoyned: and Integrity in the perſons that are to perform it.</p>
            <p>And ſo, as we have two words to enforce the duty,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Exultabit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Laetabitur.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>So we have two names to expreſs the perſons,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould begin with the duty, which is twofold;
<list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin">The duty twofold.</note> To <hi>Rejoyce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To <hi>Be glad.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
And for the better underſtanding of both, I ſhould have recourſe to the Etymology of the two words,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Shall <hi>Rejoyce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Shall <hi>be glad.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37758:36"/>
            <p>For if we will credit the judgement of <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> he doth tell us, <hi>Omnis rei inſpectio Etymologiâ cognitâ planior eſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſidorus:</note> The inſpection of every thing is beſt known by the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the word. And <hi>Plato</hi> before him gives this Rule, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Plato in Crat.</note> He that ſhall perfectly underſtand the meaning of the words, will the better come to the knowledge of the things. And the reaſon is given by <hi>Cicero;</hi> becauſe, as he ſaith,<note place="margin">Cicer. in Top.</note> 
               <hi>Verba ſunt notae rerum;</hi> Words are the ſignificant cognizances of things; And ſo, from the original of the two Verbs; with the Adverbs accompanying them, in the progreſs of our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, I ſhould make you acquainted with three things, which we are to obſerve in the duty enjoyned.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Nature of <hi>Rejoycing. &amp; Being glad.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Degree of <hi>Rejoycing. &amp; Being glad.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The Manner of <hi>Rejoycing. &amp; Being glad.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>But I am afraid I ſhould break good manners, if I ſhould enter into a degree beyond the time, which is contrary to my nature: and therefore I ſhall here break off for this time, and conclude all with a votive acclamation for the King, by whoſe returning into his Kingdoms, and to his Throne, God hath been pleaſed to turn our late captivity. Now the Acclamation which I ſhall dedicate to the King, was firſt given to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, ſometimes Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> and it is this: Carolo <hi>Auguſto, à Deo Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato, Magno &amp; Pacifico</hi> Germanorum <hi>Imperatori, Vita &amp; Victoria.</hi> Which Acclamation, ſo aſcribed to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, then Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> I may with ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration and addition, not unaptly apply, but moſt appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely attribute, to our moſt Magnificent and Puiſſant Prince, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second: who, if you will not allow him to be Emperour, yet he hath an unqueſtionable Title to be Monarch of Great <hi>Britain:</hi> and it ſhall be this; CAROLO SECUNDO, AUGUSTO, PIO, ET PACIFICO BRITANNORUM IMPERATORI, A DEO DATO, A DEO CONSERVATO, A DEO CORONATO; LONGA VITA, FELIX REGNUM, PERENNIS VICTORIA.</p>
            <div type="votive">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37758:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>TO King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, the moſt Auguſt, Pious, and Pacifick Emperour of Great</hi> Britain, <hi>Given by God to us, Preſerved by God for us, and at length, Crowned by God amongſt us; A long Life, a happy Raign; and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Victory over all his Enemies.</hi> And I hope all good Subjects will ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As for thoſe Rebells, will not ſay</hi> Amen,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let them be hang'd, I ſay, agen, agen.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <closer>God Save the KING.</closer>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Jehovae</hi> Liberatori Gloria.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glory to God, who had compaſſion on us;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And our Captivity ſo turned from us.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37758:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
